<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xml:lang="en"
         xml:id="chap-help">
  <title>Sources of help</title>

  <para>
    There is a wealth of information available about many subjects
    related to GNU/Linux. Most general documentation applies to
    Slackware Linux, because the software in the distribution has been
    compiled from source code that has been altered as little as
    possible. This chapter provides some pointers to information and
    documentation that can be found on an installed Slackware Linux
    system, and on the Internet.
  </para>

  <sect1 xml:id="chap-help-system">
    <title>On your system</title>

    <sect2 xml:id="chap-help-system-howtos">
      <title>Linux HOWTO's</title>

      <para>
        The Linux HOWTOs are a collection of documents which cover
        specific subjects related to GNU/Linux. Most Linux HOWTOs are
        not tailored to a specific distribution, therefore they are
        very useful for Slackware Linux users. The
        <emphasis>linux-howtos</emphasis> package in the
        <quote>f</quote> software set contains the HOWTO
        collection. After installing this package the HOWTOs are
        available from the <filename>/usr/doc/Linux-HOWTOs/</filename>
        directory. Slackware Linux also contains a small collection of
        Linux-related <acronym>FAQs</acronym> (FAQs are documents that
        answer Frequently Asked Questions). The Linux FAQs are
        installed to the <filename>/usr/doc/Linux-FAQs/</filename>
        directory, and are available from the
        <emphasis>linux-faqs</emphasis> package, which is also part of
        the <quote>f</quote> software set.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="chap-help-system-manpages">
      <title>Manual pages</title>

      <para>
        Most UNIX-like commands are covered by a traditional UNIX help
        system called the <emphasis>manual pages</emphasis>. You can
        read the manual page of a program with the
        <command>man</command> command. Executing
        <command>man</command> with the name of a command as an
        argument shows the manual page for that command. For instance,
      </para>

      <screen>
$ <userinput>man ls</userinput>
      </screen>

      <para>
	shows the manual page of the <command>ls</command> command.
      </para>

      <para>
	If you do not know the exact name of a manual page or command,
	you can search through the manual pages with a keyword. The
	<parameter class="command">-k</parameter> option is provided
	to make use of this facility:
      </para>

      <screen>
$ <userinput>man -k rmdir</userinput>
hrmdir               (1)  - remove an empty HFS directory
rmdir                (1)  - remove empty directories
rmdir                (2)  - delete a directory
      </screen>

      <para>
        The manual page collection is very extensive, and covers more
        subjects than just commands. The following sections of manual
        pages are available:
      </para>

      <literallayout>
1   Executable programs or shell commands
2   System calls (functions provided by the kernel)
3   Library calls (functions within program libraries)
4   Special files (usually found in /dev)
5   File formats and conventions eg /etc/passwd
6   Games
7   Miscellaneous  (including  macro  packages and conven-
    tions), e.g. man(7), groff(7)
8   System administration commands (usually only for root)
9   Linux routines [Non standard]
      </literallayout>

      <para>
        If there is more than one section that has a manual page with
        a specific name, as with for instance
        <command>rmdir</command>, you can choose what page you want to
        see by adding the section number of the manual page before the
        manual page name. For example:
      </para>

      <screen>
<userinput>man 2 rmdir</userinput>
      </screen>

      <para>
        If you would like to print a manual page to a printer that you
        have set up, you can pipe the output of <command>man</command>
        to the <command>lpr</command> command. When the <parameter
        class="command">-t</parameter> option of the
        <command>man</command> command is used, <command>man</command>
        will output the manual page in Postscript format, rather than
        ASCII. For example, you can use the following command to print
        the <command>cat</command> manual page:
      </para>

      <screen>
$ <userinput>man -t cat | lpr</userinput>
      </screen>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="chap-help-internet">
    <title>On the Internet</title>

    <para>
      There are many websites and forums related to GNU/Linux and
      Slackware Linux on the Internet. But many sites often disappear
      as fast as they appeared, and the information on many web sites
      is fragmentary. The following resources have been around for a
      longer time, and provide good content.
    </para>

    <sect2 xml:id="chap-help-internet-slacksite">
      <title>The Slackware Linux website</title>

      <para>
        The Slackware Linux website may be a bit outdated at times,
        but it provides many useful resources:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
            A news page that announces new releases and lists other
            important news that is relevant to Slackware Linux.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
            An overview of the changes to the distribution is provided
            in a structured format called a
            <emphasis>ChangeLog</emphasis>. ChangeLogs are provided
            for the current development version, as well as the latest
            stable release.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            There are two mailing lists to which you can
            subscribe. The <emphasis>slackware-announce</emphasis>
            list is used to announce new Slackware Linux releases, and
            security updates are announced on the
            <emphasis>slackware-security</emphasis> list.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A list of mirrors where you can download Slackware
            Linux. The mirrors are indexed per country. Additional
            information such as the download protocols the mirrors
            support, and the speed of the mirrors is also included.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Documentation of various kinds, including a list of
            frequently asked questions and the <emphasis>Slackware
            Linux Essentials</emphasis> book.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
	The Slackware Linux website is available at:
	<link xl:href="http://www.slackware.com/" />
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="chap-help-internet-linuxquestions">
      <title>LinuxQuestions</title>

      <para>
        LinuxQuestions is a large GNU/Linux forum with many helpful
        members.  Particularly interesting is the Slackware Linux
        subforum, where you can seek assistance to help you with
        problems that you may have with Slackware Linux. The
        LinuxQuestions forum is available at: 
	<link xl:href="http://www.linuxquestions.org/" />
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="chap-help-internet-aols">
      <title>alt.os.linux.slackware</title>

      <para>
        <emphasis>alt.os.linux.slackware</emphasis> is a Slackware
        Linux newsgroup. You can read newsgroups with a newsreader
        like tin or slrn, through the newsgroup server of your
        Internet service provider. On this newsgroup it is expected
        that you have read all necessary documentation before posting
        questions. If you have not done that, the chance of getting
        <quote>flamed</quote> is large.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
