<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
	 xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	 xml:lang="id"
	 xml:id="chap-x11">
  <title>X11</title>

  <sect1 xml:id="chap-x11-config">
    <title>X Configuration</title>

    <para>
      The X11 configuration is stored in
      <filename>/etc/X11/xorg.conf</filename>.  Many distributions
      provide special configuration tools for X, but Slackware Linux
      only provides the standard X11 tools (which are actually quite
      easy to use). In most cases X can be configured automatically,
      but sometimes it is necessary to edit
      <filename>/etc/X11/xorg.conf</filename> manually.
    </para>

    <sect2 xml:id="chap-x11-config-automatic">
      <title>Automatic configuration</title>

      <para>
	The X11 server provides an option to automatically generate a
	configuration file. X11 will load all available driver
	modules, and will try to detect the hardware, and generate a
	configuration file. Execute the following command to generate
	a <filename>xorg.conf</filename> configuration file:
      </para>

      <screen>
$ <userinput>X -configure</userinput>
      </screen>

      <para>
	If X does not output any errors, the generated configuration
	can be copied to the <filename>/etc/X11</filename>
	directory. And X can be started to test the configuration:
      </para>

      <screen>
$ <userinput>cp /root/xorg.conf /etc/X11/</userinput>
$ <userinput>startx</userinput>
      </screen>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="chap-x11-config-interactive">
      <title>Interactive configuration</title>

      <para>
	X11 provides two tools for configuring X interactively,
	<command>xorgcfg</command> and <command>xorgconfig</command>.
	<command>xorgcfg</command> tries to detect the video card
	automatically, and starts a tool which can be used to tune the
	configuration.  Sometimes <command>xorgcfg</command> switches
	to a video mode which is not supported by the monitor. In that
	case <command>xorgcfg</command> can also be used in text-mode,
	by starting it with <command>xorgcfg -textmode</command>.
      </para>

      <para>
	<command>xorgconfig</command> differs from the tools described
	above, it does not detect hardware and will ask detailed
	questions about your hardware. If you only have little
	experience configuring X11 it is a good idea to avoid
	<command>xorgconfig</command>.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="chap-x11-wm">
    <title>Window manager</title>

    <para>
      The <quote>look and feel</quote> of X11 is managed by a
      so-called window manager.  Slackware Linux provides the
      following widely-used window managers:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  WindowMaker: A relatively light window manager, which is
	  part of the GNUStep project.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  BlackBox: Light window manager, BlackBox has no dependencies
	  except the X11 libraries.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  KDE: A complete desktop environment, including browser,
	  e-mail program and an office suite (KOffice).
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Xfce: A lightweight desktop environment. This is an ideal
	  environment if you would like to have a userfriendly desktop
	  that runs on less capable machines.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      If you are used to a desktop environment, using KDE or Xfce is a
      logical choice. But it is a good idea to try some of the lighter
      window managers. They are faster, and consume less memory,
      besides that most KDE and Xfce applications are perfectly usable
      under other window managers.
    </para>

    <para>
      On Slackware Linux the <command>xwmconfig</command> command can
      be used to set the default window manager. This program shows
      the installed window managers, from which you can choose
      one. You can set the window manager globally by executing
      <command>xwmconfig</command> as root.
    </para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
