<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
	 xml:id="chap-intro">
  <title>Una introducción a Slackware Linux</title>

  <sect1 xml:id="chap-intro-linux">
    <title>Qué es Linux?</title>

    <para>
      Linux es un kernel UNIX-like, escrito por Linus Torvalds y 
      otros desarrolladores. Linux se ejecuta en diversas arquitecturas,
      como por ejemplo IA32, IA64, Alpha, m68k, SPARC y máquinas
      PowerPC. La última versión e información sobre el kernel Linux
      pueden ser encontradas en el sitio: <ulink
      url="http://www.kernel.org">http://www.kernel.org</ulink>.
    </para>

    <para>
      El kernel Linux es usualmente confundido con el sistema operativo
      GNU/Linux. Linux es solamente el kernel, no un sistema operativo
      completo. GNU/Linux se compone de el sistema operativo GNU con
      el kernel Linux. La siguiente sección brinda una descripción 
      mas completa sobre GNU/Linux.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="chap-intro-gnulinux">
    <title>Qué es GNU/Linux?</title>

    <para>
      En 1984, Richar Stallman inició un proyecto ambicioso con el
      objetivo de escribir un sistema operativo UNIX-like libre. El
      nombre de este sistema es <acronym>GNU</acronym>, que es un 
      acrónimo de <quote>GNU's Not UNIX (GNU no es UNIX)</quote>.
      A mediados de 1990, la mayoría de los componentes del sistema
      operativo GNU fueron escritos, a excepción del kernel. Dos
      años antes, en 1988, se decidió que el proyecto GNU usaría el
      microkernel Mach 3.0 como base de su kernel. Entretanto, tomó
      hasta 1991 para que Mach 3.0 fuese liberado bajo una licencia
      de software libre. En el mismo año, Linus Torvalds comenzó a 
      construir un kernel para el sistema GNU, el kernel Linux. Es 
      por esto que GNU/Linux referencia un sistema GNU ejecutándose
      con el kernel Linux.
    </para>

    <para>
      El kernel GNU, denominado <quote>HURD</quote> estaba aún en 
      desarrollo cuando este libro fué escrito, pero está disponible
      como el sistema operativo GNU/HURD. Existen otros kernels que
      han sido portados al sistema operativo GNU. Por ejemplo, el
      proyecto Debian ha desarrollado una versión del sistema 
      operativo GNU que funciona con el kernel NetBSD.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="chap-intro-slackware">
    <title>Qué es Slackware Linux?</title>

    <para>
      Slackware Linux is a GNU/Linux distribution, which is maintained
      and developed by Patrick Volkerding. A distribution is a
      coherent collection of software that provides a usable GNU/Linux
      system. Volkerding started using GNU/Linux because he needed a
      LISP interpreter for a project. At the time the dominant
      GNU/Linux distribution was Softlanding System Linux (SLS
      Linux). Slackware Linux started out as a private collection of
      Volkerding's patches for SLS Linux. The first publicly available
      Slackware Linux release was 1.0, which was released on July 16,
      1993.
    </para>

    <para>
      In contrast to many other GNU/Linux distributions, Slackware
      Linux adheres to the so-called KISS (Keep It Simple Stupid)
      principle. This means that Slackware Linux does not have complex
      graphical tools to configure the system. As a result the
      learning curve of Slackware Linux can be high for inexperienced
      GNU/Linux users, but it provides more transparency and
      flexibility. Besides that you get a deeper understanding of
      GNU/Linux with no-frills distributions like Slackware Linux.
    </para>

    <para>
      Another distinguishing aspect of Slackware Linux, that also
      <quote>complies</quote> with the KISS principle, is the
      Slackware Linux package manager. Slackware Linux does not have a
      complex package manager like RPM or dpkg. Packages are normal
      tgz (tar/gzip) files, often with an additional installation
      script and a package description file. For novice users tgz is
      much more powerful than RPM, and avoids dependency
      problems. Another widely known feature of Slackware Linux is its
      initialization scripts. In contrast to most other GNU/Linux
      distributions Slackware Linux does not have a directory for each
      runlevel with symbolic links to services that have to be started
      or killed in that runlevel. It uses a simpler approach in which
      you can enable or disable services by twiddling the executable
      bit of an initialization script.
    </para>

    <para>
      The packages in Slackware Linux are compiled with as little
      modifications as possible. This means you can use most general
      GNU/Linux documentation.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="chap-intro-unix">
    <title>The UNIX philosophy</title>

    <para>
      Since GNU/Linux is a free reimplementation of the UNIX operating
      system, it is a good idea to look at the philosophy that made
      UNIX widely loved.  Doug McIlroy summarized the UNIX philosophy
      in three simple rules:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Write programs that do one thing and do it well.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Write programs to work together.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Write programs to handle text streams, because that is a
          universal interface.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      Odds are that you do not intend to write programs for
      GNU/Linux. However, even as a user these basic UNIX rules can
      mean a lot to you. Once you get to know the essential commands
      that have been part of UNIX for many years, you will be able to
      combine simple programs to solve complex problems. Keep this in
      mind while you learn Slackware Linux; try to get a feeling for
      how you can divide complex tasks in simple combined operations.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="free-software">
    <title>Free and open source software</title>

    <para>
      Most packages in Slackware Linux are published under a free
      software or open source license. Under these licenses software
      may be used, studied, changed and distributed
      freely. Practically, this means that the software is available
      and redistributable in source and binary form. Although the free
      software and open source software movements share many licenses
      and principles, there are subtle differences between both
      movements. The open source movement tends to focus on the
      economic and technical advantages of sharing source code, while
      the free software movement puts accent on the ethical side of
      providing sources and binaries freely. As the GNU website puts
      it: <quote>Free software is a matter of liberty, not price.  To
      understand the concept, you should think of free as in free
      speech, not as in free beer.<footnote>
      <para>
	<ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.html" />
      </para>
    </footnote></quote>

      In the spirit of free and open source software the source code
      of almost all packages is included in the official Slackware
      Linux CD set or DVD.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="slackware-features">
    <title>Slackware Linux 12.0 features</title>

    <para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Linux 2.6.21.5</emphasis> -
	    Slackware Linux uses as modern high-performance Linux
	    kernel. The kernel includes support for all modern disk
	    controllers, LVM, Software RAID, encrypted disks, and
	    multiple processors/cores. By default,
	    <emphasis>udev</emphasis> is enabled for automatic
	    management of device nodes.
          </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis role="bold">HAL</emphasis> - the HAL (Hardware
	    Abstraction Layer) is now included too. This provides a
	    uniform API for desktop applications to use hardware.  It
	    makes automatic mounting of disks and CDs considerably
	    easier under Xfce and KDE.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">X11 7.2.0</emphasis> - This is the
            first version of Slackware Linux to use modular X.  This
            means that the X11 components are separated in many small
            packages for easier maintenance and lighter weight
            upgrades.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">GCC 4.1.2</emphasis> - Slackware
            Linux 12.0 includes a completely revised toolchain based
            on the GNU Compiler Collection 4.1.2. GCC provides C, C++,
            Objective-C, Fortran-77/95, and Ada 95
            compilers. Additionally, version 2.5 of the GNU C library is
            used.
          </para>
        </listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Apache 2.2.4</emphasis> - Apache was
	    upgraded to a new major version. Apache 2.x is a
	    substantial rewrite of the old 1.3.x series.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">The K Desktop Environment (KDE)
            3.5.7</emphasis> - The full KDE environment is provided,
            which includes KOffice, the Konqueror web browser,
            multimedia programs, development tools, and many more
            useful applications.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Xfce 4.4.1</emphasis> - Xfce is a
            lightweight desktop environment based on GTK2. It embodies
            the UNIX spirit of modularity and reusability.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para> 
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="chap-intro-getting">
    <title>Getting Slackware Linux</title>

    <para>
      Slackware Linux is freely downloadable from the official
      Slackware Linux mirrors. The list of Slackware mirrors is
      available at <ulink url="http://www.slackware.com/getslack/" />.
    </para>

    <para>
      You can also order Slackware Linux as a CD set or DVD from the
      Slackware Store.  Many Internet shops also provide Slackware
      Linux cheaply on CD-ROM or DVD, but you are only supporting
      Slackware Linux financially if you buy an official CD set or
      DVD. The Slackware Store also offers Slackware Linux
      subscriptions.  A subscriber automatically receives new
      Slackware Linux releases at a reduced price.
    </para>

    <para>
      If you would like to have more information about purchasing
      Slackware Linux, visit the Slackware Store website at <ulink
      url="http://store.slackware.com/" />.
    </para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
