<!-- $Id: mutt.xml 333 2007-10-21 17:20:54Z danieldk $ -->

<chapter id="email-mutt"> <?dbhtml filename="mutt.html"?>
  <title>Leyendo y escribiendo email con mutt</title>

  <indexterm><primary>mutt</primary></indexterm>

  <sect1 id="email-mutt-introduction">
    <title>Introducción</title>

    <indexterm><primary>MUA</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>Mail User Agent</primary></indexterm>

    <para>
      Mutt es un agente usuario de correo (<acronym>MUA</acronym>,
      mail user agent) que puede ser utilizado para leer y escribir
      e-mail. Mutt se instala en modo texto, esto significa que puede
      ser utilizado en la consola, sobre SSH y en una terminal
      X. Debido a su interfaz de menú, es muy fácil leer grandes
      cantidades de e-mail en corto tiempo, y mutt puede configurarse
      para utilizar su editor de texto preferido.
    </para>

    <para>
      En este capítulo hablaremos sobre como puede personalizar mutt a
      sus necesidades, como utilizarlo, y como el soporte PGP/GnuPG es
      utilizado.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="email-mutt-usage">
    <title>Uso</title>

    <para>
      Mutt es bastante simple de usar, a pesar de que puede tomar
      algún tiempo acostumbrarse a las teclas usadas para navegación,
      lectura y escritura de e-mails. Las siguientes secciones
      describen algunas de las teclas más importantes. Mutt provee un
      resumen mas completo de las teclas disponibles después de
      presionar la tecla &lt;h&gt;.
    </para>

    <sect2 id="email-mutt-usage-browsing">
      <title>Navegando por la lista de e-mails</title>
      
      <para>
	Después de invocar el comando <command>mutt</command>, se
	mostrará un resumen de todos los e-mails. Puede navegar a
	través de la lista de e-mails con las teclas direccionales
	arriba y abajo, o las teclas &lt;k&gt; y &lt;j&gt;.
      </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="email-mutt-usage-reading">
      <title>Leyendo e-mails</title>
      
      <para>
	Para leer un e-mail, utilice la tecla &lt;Enter&gt; después de
	seleccionar un e-mail de la lista de e-mails.  Cuando esté
	leyendo un e-mail puede utilizar la tecla &lt;Page Up&gt; y
	&lt;Page Down&gt; para navegar a través del e-mail. Todavía
	puede utilizar las teclas de navegación para navegar a través
	de los e-mails de la lista.
      </para>

      <para>
	Si un e-mail tiene datos adjuntos, puede verlos presionando la
	tecla &lt;v&gt;. Puede ver los adjuntos individuales
	seleccionándolos y presionando la tecla &lt;Enter&gt;. Para
	guardar un adjunto en un archivo, presione la tecla &lt;s&gt;.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2 id="email-mutt-usage-sending">
      <title>Enviando e-mails</title>

      <para>
	Puede crear un email con la tecla &lt;m&gt; o responder a un
	e-mail seleccionado con la tecla &lt;r&gt;. Mutt le pedirá
	especificar el recipiente (<emphasis>To:</emphasis>), y el
	tema (<emphasis>Subject:</emphasis>). Después de ingresar esta
	información se ejecutará un editor(<command>vi</command> es
	usado por defecto), el cual puede usar para componer el
	e-mail. Después de guardar el e-mail y abandonar el editor,
	mutt le dará la oportunidad de realizar cambios al e-mail. Si
	decide alterar el e-mail, puede reiniciar el editor con la
	tecla &lt;e&gt;. Puede cambiar el recipiente o el tema con
	&lt;t&gt; o &lt;s&gt;. Finalmente, puede enviar el e-mail
	presionando &lt;y&gt;. Si quisiera cancelar el e-mail,
	presione &lt;q&gt; Mutt preguntará si quiere posponer el
	e-mail. Si asi lo desea, tendrá la oportunidad de rehacer el
	e-mail la próxima vez que cree un mensaje.
      </para>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="email-mutt-basicsetup">
    <title>Configuración basica</title>

    <para>
      There are a few mutt settings you often want to configure. This section
      describes these settings. User-specific mutt customizations can be made
      in the <filename>.muttrc</filename> in the user's home directory. You
      can change global mutt settings in <filename>/etc/mutt/Muttrc</filename>.
    </para>

    <sect2 id="email-mutt-basicsetup-headers">
      <title>Customized headers</title>

      <indexterm><primary>mutt</primary><secondary>headers</secondary></indexterm>

      <para>
        Each e-mail has headers with various information. For example, the
        header contains information about the path an e-mail has traversed
        after it has been sent. The sender (<emphasis>From:</emphasis>) and
        recipient (<emphasis>To:</emphasis>) e-mail addresses are also stored
        in the headers, as well as the subject (<emphasis>Subject:</emphasis>)
        of an e-mail.
      </para>

      <note>
        <para>
          In reality the <emphasis>To:</emphasis> header is not used to
          determine the destination of an e-mail during the deliverance
          process of the e-mail. MTAs use the <emphasis>envelope
          address</emphasis> to determine the destination of the e-mail.
          Though, most MUAs use the <emphasis>To:</emphasis> address that
          the user fills in as the envelope address.
        </para>
      </note>

      <para>
        You can add your own headers to an e-mail with the
        <emphasis>my_hdr</emphasis> configuration option. This option
        has the following syntax: <emphasis>my_hdr &lt;header name&gt;:
        &lt;header contents&gt;</emphasis>. For example, you can add information
        about what OS you are running by adding the following line to your
        mutt configuration:
      </para>

      <screen>
my_hdr X-Operating-System: Slackware Linux 10.2
      </screen>

      <para>
        You can also override some of the headers that are normally used,
        such as the sender address that is specified in the
        <emphasis>From:</emphasis> header:
      </para>

      <screen>
my_hdr From: John Doe &lt;john.doe@example.org&gt;
      </screen>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>The sendmail binary</title>

      <indexterm><primary>mutt</primary><secondary>sendmail binary</secondary></indexterm>

      <para>
        By default mutt uses the sendmail MTA to deliver e-mails that
        were sent. You can use another command to send e-mail by altering
        the <emphasis>sendmail</emphasis> configuration variable. The
        sendmail replacement must handle the same parameter syntax
        as sendmail. For example, if you have installed MSMTP to deliver
        e-mails, you can configure mutt to use it by adding the following
        line to your mutt configuration:
      </para>

      <screen>
set sendmail="/usr/bin/msmtp"
      </screen>

      <para>
        When you have completely replaced sendmail with another MTA, for
        instance Postfix, it is usually not needed to set this parameter,
        because most MTAs provide an alternative sendmail binary file.
      </para>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="email-mutt-imap">
    <title>Using IMAP</title>

    <para>
      Normally, mutt reads e-mail from the user's local spool mailbox.
      However, mutt also has support for using IMAP mailboxes.
      <acronym>IMAP</acronym> (the Internet Message Access Protocol)
      is a protocol that is used for accessing e-mail from a remote
      server, and is supported by many e-mail servers. Mutt uses the
      following URL format for representing IMAP servers:
    </para>

    <literallayout>
imap://[user@]hostname[:port]/[mailbox]
    </literallayout>

    <para>
      Or the following format for IMAP over SSL/TLS:
    </para>
    
    <literallayout>
imaps://[user@]hostname[:port]/[mailbox]
    </literallayout>

    <para>
      You can directly use this syntax in folder-related operatings.
      For example, if you press <quote>c</quote> to change from folder,
      you can enter an IMAP URL. This is a bit tedious, so it is easier
      to store this information in your <filename>.muttrc</filename> file.
    </para>

    <para>
      If you use only one IMAP account, you can set the INBOX folder
      of this account as the spool mailbox, and the main IMAP account
      as the e-mail folder. For example, adding the following lines
      to your <filename>.muttrc</filename> configuration file will set
      up mutt to log in to the <emphasis>imap.example.org</emphasis>
      server as the <emphasis>me</emphasis> user.
    </para>

    <screen>
set folder=imap://me@imap.example.org/
set spoolfile=imap://me@imap.example.org/INBOX
    </screen>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="email-mutt-gnupg">
    <title>Signing/encrypting e-mails</title>

    <sect2 id="email-mutt-gnupg-introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <para>
        Mutt provides excellent support for signing or encrypting e-mails
        with GnuPG. One might wonder why he or she should use one of these
        techniques. While most people do not feel the need to encrypt most
        of their e-mails, it generally is a good idea to sign your e-mails.
        There are, for example, a lot of viruses these days that use other
        people's e-mail addresses in the From: field of viruses. If the
        people who you are communicating with know that you sign your e-mails,
        they will not open fake e-mail from viruses. Besides that it looks
        much more professional if people can check your identity, especially
        in business transactions. For example, who would you rather trust,
        vampire_boy93853@hotmail.com, or someone using a professional e-mail
        address with digitally signed e-mails?
      </para>

      <para>
        This section describes how you can use GnuPG with mutt, for more
        information about GnuPG read
        <xref linkend="basics-filesystem-gnupg" />.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="email-mutt-gnupg-configuration">
      <title>Configuration</title>

      <para>
        An example configuration for using GnuPG in mutt can be found
        in <filename>/usr/share/doc/mutt/samples/gpg.rc</filename>.
        In general the contents of this file to your mutt configuration will
        suffice. From the shell you can add the contents of this file
        to you <filename>.muttrc</filename> with the following command:
      </para>

      <screen>
$ <command>cat /usr/share/doc/mutt/samples/gpg.rc >> ~/.muttrc</command>
      </screen>

      <para>
        There are some handy parameters that you can additionally set.
        For example, if you always want to sign e-mails, add the following
        line to your mutt configuration:
      </para>

      <screen>
set crypt_autosign = yes
      </screen>

      <para>
        Another handy option is <emphasis>crypt_replyencrypt</emphasis>,
        which will automatically encrypt replies to messages that were
        encrypted. To enable this, add the following line to your mutt
        configuration:
      </para>

      <screen>
set crypt_replyencrypt = yes
      </screen>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="email-mutt-gnupg-usage">
      <title>Usage</title>

      <para>
        If you have set some of the automatic options, like
        <emphasis>crypt_autosign</emphasis>, GnuPG usage of mutt is mostly
        automatic. If not, you can press the &lt;p&gt; key during the
        final step of sending an e-mail. In the bottom of the screen
        various GnuPG/PGP options will appear, which you can access
        via the letters that are enclosed in parentheses. For example,
        &lt;s&gt; signs e-mails, and &lt;e&gt; encrypts an e-mail.
        You can always clear any GnuPG option you set by pressing
        &lt;p&gt; and then &lt;c&gt;.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

</chapter>
