<!-- $Id: bind.xml,v 1.4 2004/12/19 10:19:33 daniel Exp $ -->

<chapter> <?dbhtml filename="bind.html"?>
<title>BIND</title>

<sect1>
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
The domain name system (<acronym>DNS</acronym>) is used to convert
human-friendly host names (for example www.slackware.com) to IP
addresses. <acronym>BIND</acronym> (Berkeley Internet Name Domain) is
the most widely used DNS daemon, and will be covered in this chapter.
</para>

<sect2>
<title>Delegation</title>

<para>
One of the main features is that DNS requests can be delegated. For example,
suppose that you own the <quote>linuxcorp.com</quote> domain. You can provide
the authorized nameservers for this domain, you nameservers are authorative
for the <quote>linuxcorp.com</quote>. Suppose that there are different
branches within your company, and you want to give each branch authority
over their own zone, that is no problem with DNS. You can delegate DNS
for e.g. <quote>sales.linuxcorp.com</quote> to another nameserver within
the DNS configuration for the <quote>linuxcorp.com</quote> zone.
</para>

<para>
The DNS system has so-called root servers, which delegate the DNS for
millions of domain names and extensions (for example, country specific
extensions, like <quote>.nl</quote> or <quote>.uk</quote>) to authorized
DNS servers. This system allows a branched tree of delegation, which is
very flexible, and distributes DNS traffic.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>DNS records</title>

<para>
The following types are common DNS records:
</para>

<table>
<title>DNS records</title>
<tgroup cols="2">
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Prefix</entry><entry>Description</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>A</entry><entry>An A records points to an IP address.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>CNAME</entry><entry>A CNAME record points to another DNS entry.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>MX</entry><entry>A MX record specifies which should handle mail for 
the domain.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Masters and slaves</title>

<para>
Two kinds of nameservers can be provided for a domain name: a master and
slaves. The master server DNS records are authorative. Slave servers download
their DNS record from the master servers. Using slave servers besides a
master server is recommended for high availability and can be used for
load-balancing.
</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Making a caching nameserver</title>

<para>
A caching nameserver provides DNS services for a machine or a network,
but does not provide DNS for a domain. That means it can only be used
to convert hostnames to IP addresses. Setting up a nameserver with
&Distribution; is fairly easy, because BIND is configured as a
caching nameserver by default. Enabling the caching nameserver takes
just two steps: you have to install BIND and alter the initialization
scripts. BIND can be installed by adding the bind package from
the <quote>n</quote> disk set. After that bind can be started by executing the
<command>named(8)</command> command. If want to start BIND by
default, make the <filename>/etc/rc.d/rc.bind</filename> file executable.
This can be done by executing the following command as root:
</para>

<screen>
# <command>chmod a+x /etc/rc.d/rc.bind</command>
</screen>

<para>
If you want to use the nameserver on the machine that runs BIND,
you also have to alter <filename>/etc/resolv.conf</filename>.
</para>

</sect1>

</chapter>
