<!-- $Id: concepts.xml,v 1.6 2005/03/02 08:24:27 daniel Exp $ -->

<chapter> <?dbhtml filename="concepts.html"?>
<title>General concepts</title>

<para>
This chapter gives an introduction to some general Unix and &OS;
concepts. It is a good idea to read this chapter thoroughly if you
do not have any UNIX or &OS; experience. Many concepts covered in this
chapter are used in this book and in &OS;.
</para>

<sect1>
<title>Multitasking</title>

<sect2>
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
One of &Kernel;' strengths is multi-tasking. Multi-tasking means that multiple
processes can run at the same time. You might wonder why this is important
to you, because most people are using one application at a time. Besides
the more obvious reason that it is just handy to browse while you have a
word processor running in the background, multi-tasking is a bare necessity
for Unix-like systems. Even if you have launched no applications there are
a bunch of processes running in the background. Some processes might provide
network services, others sit there showing a login prompt on other consoles,
and there is even a process that executes scheduled tasks. These processes
that are running in the background are often called <emphasis>daemon</emphasis>
(not to be confused with the word demon, a daemon is a protective angel).
At a later stage we are going to look at how you can move processes to the
background yourself (see <xref linkend="chap-proc" />).
</para>

<note>
<para>
Note that on single-processor systems processes are not really running
simultaneously. In reality a smart scheduler in the kernel is dividing
CPU time between processes, giving the illusion that processes are
running simultaneously.
</para>
</note>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Processes and threads</title>

<para>
Applications run as one or more processes. To see what a process
actually is we need to know what it consists of. Every process
basically has two areas; an area that is named
<emphasis>text</emphasis> and an area that is named
<emphasis>data</emphasis>.  The <emphasis>text</emphasis> area is the
actual program code; it is used to tell the computer what to
do. The <emphasis>data</emphasis> area is used to store information
that the process has to keep. The operating system makes sure that
every process gets its time to execute. New processes can be created
by duplicating a running process with a system call named 
<emphasis>fork</emphasis>. <xref linkend="fork" /> shows a fork in action
schematically. The parent process issues a <emphasis>fork()</emphasis>
call, and as a result a new process is created.
</para>

<figure id="fork">
<title>Forking a process</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/fork.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
The problem with processes is that they can get quite large, and
that is not very efficient for computers with more than one processor.
This problem is solved by duplicating the <emphasis>text</emphasis> area
of a process. So, a threaded process is basically a program that has
multiple instances of its executing code running, but these instances
share the data area of the process (unlike a fork). These threads can
be divided over multiple CPUs, making it possible to run one process
on more than one CPU simultaneously.
</para>
</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Filesystem hierarchy</title>

<sect2>
<title>Structure</title>

<para>
Operating systems store data in filesystems. A filesystem is basically
a collection of directories that hold files, like the operating system,
user programs and user data. In &OS; there is only one filesystem
hierarchy, this means &OS; doesn't have multiple drives (e.g. A:,
C:, D:), like Windows. The filesystem looks like a tree, with a root
directory (<filename>/</filename>) which has no parent directory, branches, 
and leaves (directories with no subdirectories). Directories are separated
using the <quote>/</quote> character.
</para>

<figure id="filesystem-structure">
<title>The filesystem structure</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/fs-structure.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
<xref linkend="filesystem-structure"/> shows the structure of a filesystem.
You can see that the root directory (<filename>/</filename>) has two child
directories; <filename>bin</filename> and <filename>home</filename>. The
<filename>home</filename> directory has two child directories, 
<filename>joe</filename> and <filename>jack</filename>. The diagram shows
the full pathname of each directory. The same notation is used for files.
Suppose that there is a file named <filename>memo.txt</filename> in
the <filename>/home/jack</filename> directory, the full path of the
file is <filename>/home/jack/memo.txt</filename>.
</para>

<para>
Each directory has to special entries, <quote><filename>.</filename></quote>,
and <quote><filename>..</filename></quote>. 
<quote><filename>.</filename></quote> refers to the same directory,
<quote><filename>..</filename></quote> to the parent directory. These
entries can be used for making relative paths. Suppose that you are working
in the <filename>jack</filename> directory. From this directory you can
reference to the <filename>joe</filename> directory with 
<filename>../joe</filename>.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Mounting</title>

<para>
You might have started to wonder how it is possible to access other devices
or partitions than the hard disk partition which holds the root filesystem.
&Kernel; uses the same approach as UNIX for accessing other mediums. &Kernel;
allows the system administrator to connect a device to any directory in
the filesystem structure. This process is named <quote>mounting</quote>.
For example, one could mount the CD-ROM drive to the 
<filename>/cdrom</filename> directory. If the mount was correct, the files
on the CD-ROM can be accessed through this directory. The mounting
process is described in detail in <xref linkend="mounting"/>.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Common directories</title>

<para>
The Filesystem Hierarchy Standard Group has attempted to create a
standard that describes which directories should be available on a
&OS; system.  Nowadays most major distributions use the
Filesystem Hierarchy Standard (<acronym>FHS</acronym>) as a
guideline. This section describes some mandatory directories on
&OS; systems.
</para>

<para>
Please note that &OS; does not have a separate directory for each
application (like Windows), files are ordered by function and type. For
example, the binaries for most common user programs are stored in
<filename>/usr/bin</filename>, and their libraries in 
<filename>/usr/lib</filename>. This is a short overview of important
directories:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">/bin</emphasis>: essential
user binaries that should still be available in case the 
<filename>/usr</filename> is not mounted.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">/dev</emphasis>: device files.
These are special files used to access certain devices.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">/etc</emphasis>: the <filename>/etc</filename>
directory contains all important configuration files.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">/home</emphasis>: contains home directories for
individual users.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">/lib</emphasis>: essential system libraries (like glibc),
and kernel modules.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">/root</emphasis>: home directory for the 
<emphasis>root</emphasis> user.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">/sbin</emphasis>: essential binaries that are used for
system administration.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">/tmp</emphasis>: a world-writable directory for
temporary files.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">X11R6</emphasis>: the X Window System.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">/usr/bin</emphasis>: stores the majority of the
user binaries.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">/usr/lib</emphasis>: libraries that are not essential
for the system to boot.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">/usr/sbin</emphasis>: non-essential system administration
binaries.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">/var</emphasis>: variable data files, like logs.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Devices</title>

<sect2>
<title>Introduction</title>
<para>
In UNIX and &Kernel; almost everything is represented as a file, including
devices. Each &OS; system has a a directory with special files, named
<filename>/dev</filename>. Each file in the <filename>/dev</filename>
directory represents a device. You might wonder how this is done; a
device file is a special file because it has two special numbers, the
<emphasis>major</emphasis> and the <emphasis>minor</emphasis> number.
The kernel knows which device a device file represents by these numbers.
The following example shows these numbers for a device:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>ls -l /dev/zero</command> 
crw-rw-rw-    1 root     root       1,   5 Apr 22  2003 /dev/zero
</screen>

<para>
The <command>ls</command> lists files and information about files. In this
example information about the <filename>/dev/zero</filename> device is
listed. This particular device has <emphasis>1</emphasis> as the major
device number, and <emphasis>5</emphasis> as the minor device number.
</para>

<note>
<para>
If you have the kernel sources unpacked after installing &Distribution;, you
can find a comprehensive list of all major devices with their minor
and major numbers in 
<filename>/usr/src/linux/Documentation/devices.txt</filename>. An
up-to-date list is also available online at:
<ulink url="ftp://ftp.kernel.org/pub/linux/docs/device-list/" />
</para>
</note>

<para>
For the &Kernel; kernel there are two types of devices: 
<emphasis>character</emphasis> and <emphasis>block</emphasis> devices.
Character devices can be read byte by byte, block devices can not. Block
devices are read per block (for example 4096 bytes at a time). Whether
a device is a character or block device is determined by the nature of
the device. For example, most storage media are block devices, and most
input devices are character devices. Block devices have one distinctive
advantage, namely that they can be cached. This means that commonly read
or written blocks are stored in a special area of the system memory, named
the cache. Memory is much faster than most storage media, so it is a
huge performance benefit to perform read and write operations on commonly
used blocks in memory. Of course, eventually changes have to be written to 
the storage medium.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>ATA and SCSI devices</title>

<para>
There are two categories of devices that we are going to look into in detail, 
because understanding the naming of these devices can be crucial for 
partitioning a hard disk, or for mounting. Almost all modern computers use
ATA hard disks and CD-ROMs. Under &Kernel; these devices are named in the 
following way:
</para>

<screen>
/dev/hda - master device on the first ATA channel
/dev/hdb - slave device on the first ATA channel
/dev/hdc - master device on the second ATA channel
/dev/hdd - slave device on the second ATA channel
</screen>

<para>
On most computers the hard disk is the master device on the first ATA
channel (<filename>/dev/hda</filename>), and the CD-ROM the master
device on the second ATA channel. Hard disk partitions have the device
name plus a number. For example, <filename>/dev/hda1</filename> is the
first partition on the <filename>/dev/hda</filename> disk. 
</para>

<para>
Most average PCs do not have SCSI hard disks or CD-ROM drives, but SCSI is 
often used for USB drives. Besides that Serial ATA (SATA) drives are also
made available as SCSI disks. For SCSI drives the following notation is used:
</para>

<screen>
/dev/sda - First SCSI disk
/dev/sdb - Second SCSI disk
/dev/sdc - Third SCSI disk
/dev/scd0 - First CD-ROM
/dev/scd1 - Second CD-ROM
/dev/scd2 - Third CD-ROM
</screen>

<para>
Partitions are notated in the same way as ATA disks; 
<filename>/dev/sda1</filename> is the first partition on the first SCSI
disk.
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

</chapter>
