<!-- $Id: help.xml,v 1.6 2004/12/19 10:19:33 daniel Exp $ -->

<chapter> <?dbhtml filename="help.html"?>
<title>Sources of help</title>

<sect1>
<title>On your system</title>

<sect2>
<title>&Kernel; HOWTO's</title>

<para>
The famous &Kernel; HOWTOs are a collection of documents which
cover specific parts of a &OS; system. Most HOWTOs are
distribution independent, and therefore very useful for using
them with &Distribution;. The "linux-howtos" package in
from the <quote>f</quote> diskset contains the HOWTO collection. After
installing this package the HOWTOs can be found in
the <filename>/usr/doc/&Kernel;-HOWTOs/</filename> directory.
&Distribution; also contains a collection of Mini-HOWTOs, which
are shorter and cover narrower topics. The Mini-HOWTOs can
be found in the <filename>/usr/doc/&Kernel;-mini-HOWTOs/</filename>
directory after installing the <quote>linux-mini-howtos</quote> package.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Manual pages</title>

<para>
Most Unix-like commands are covered by the a traditional *nix
help system called the manual pages. You can read the manual
page of a program by using the <command>man</command> command.
Executing <command>man</command> with the name of the command
as a parameter shows the manual page for that command. For example:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>man ls</command>
</screen>

<para>
If you do not know the exact name of a manual page or command, you can
search a page using the keyword (<emphasis>-k</emphasis>) parameter:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>man -k routing</command>
NETLINK_ROUTE [rtnetlink] (7)  - &Kernel; IPv4 routing socket
netstat              (8)  - Print network connections, routing tables, interface statistics, masquerade connections, and multicast memberships
route                (8)  - show / manipulate the IP routing table
routed               (8)  - network routing daemon
rtnetlink            (7)  - &Kernel; IPv4 routing socket
</screen>

<para>
We have to add that there are also manual pages that cover other things
than commands. These sections of manual pages are available:
</para>

<screen>
1   Executable programs or shell commands
2   System calls (functions provided by the kernel)
3   Library calls (functions within program libraries)
4   Special files (usually found in /dev)
5   File formats and conventions eg /etc/passwd
6   Games
7   Miscellaneous  (including  macro  packages and conven-
    tions), e.g. man(7), groff(7)
8   System administration commands (usually only for root)
9   Kernel routines [Non standard]
</screen>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>On the internet</title>

<bridgehead>alt.os.linux.slackware</bridgehead>

<para>
alt.os.linux.slackware is a &Distribution; newsgroup. You can read
newsgroups with a newsreader like tin or knode. Be careful: it is
expected that you have read all necessary documentation before posting
to this newsgroup. If you have not the chance of getting <quote>flamed</quote>
is really big.
</para>

</sect1>

</chapter>
