<!-- $Id: introduction.xml,v 1.5 2004/12/18 22:14:34 daniel Exp $ -->

<chapter> <?dbhtml filename="introduction.html"?>
<title>An introduction to &Distribution;</title>

<sect1>
<title>What is Linux?</title>

<para>
Linux is a Unix-like kernel which is written by Linus Torvalds
and other developers, who communicate using the internet. Linux
runs on many different architectures, for example on many IA32, IA64,
Alpha, m68k, SPARC and PowerPC machines. The latest kernel and
more information can be found at:
<ulink url="http://www.kernel.org">http://www.kernel.org</ulink>
</para>

<para>
Linux is often confused with the &OS; system. Linux is only a
kernel, not a complete operating system. &OS; consists of the
GNU operating system with the Linux kernel. Please read the following
section for a more detailed explanation of &OS;.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>What is &OS;?</title>

<para>
At the beginning of the eighties Richard Stallman started an ambitious
project with the goal to write a free Unix-like operating system. The
name of this system is <acronym>GNU</acronym> (GNU is Not Unix). At
the  beginning of the nineties most important components of the GNU
oparating system were written, except for the kernel, which is still
under development under the name HURD. HURD consists of some servers
which provide Unix-like kernel functionality. In turn these servers
run under the Mach microkernel.  At the beginning at the nineties the
HURD team still had to wait till the Mach sources were released as
free software. In the meanwhile Linus started filling the gap with the
Linux kernel. &OS; thus refers to the GNU system running on the
Linux kernel. Right now the HURD kernel is also in a usable state and
can be downloaded in the form of the GNU/HURD operating system. The
<ulink url="http://www.debian.org/">Debian</ulink> project has even
developed a version of the GNU operating system which works with the
<ulink url="http://www.netbsd.org/">NetBSD</ulink> kernel. We should
call "Linux distributions" "&OS; distributions", because GNU is a
substantial part of most distributions.  </para> </sect1>

<sect1>
<title>What is &Distribution;?</title>

<para>
&Distribution; is a &OS; distribution which is maintained and
developed by Patrick Volkerding. In contrast to many other distributions
&Distribution; adheres to the so-called KISS (keep it simple stupid) principle.
This means that &Distribution; does not have complex graphical tools for
configuring a system. For newbies this can be somwhat harsh, but it
provides more transperancy and flexibility. Besides that you will
get to learn &OS; to the bones with &Distribution;.
</para>

<para>
Another distinguishing aspect of &Distribution;, that also "complies"
with the KISS principe is the &Distribution; package manager. &Distribution; 
does not have complex package manager like RPM. Packages are normal tgz
(tar/gzip) files, mostly with an additional installation script and
a package description. Tgz is much more powerful than RPM for novice
users and avoids dependency problems. Another famous feature of &Distribution; 
are the BSD-like initialization scripts of &Distribution;. &Distribution; 
has one initialization script for each runlevel insteas of a script
for eacht daemon. It allow you to tweak with your system easily,
without the need to write net init scripts yourself.
</para>

<para>
The packages in &Distribution; are compiled with as little modifications
as possible. This means you can use most general &OS; documentation.
</para>  

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>&Distribution; on CD-ROM</title>
<para>
&Distribution; can be purchased at quite many (internet) shops. It is
important to make a distinction between the official CD-ROM set and
cheap copies. When you buy the official CD set you are financially
supporting the development of &Distribution;. So, if you would
like to see continuing development of &Distribution;, buy the CD set!
The Slackware Store can be found at: 
<ulink url="http://store.slackware.com/" />
</para>

</sect1>

</chapter>
