<!-- $Id: ipsec.xml,v 1.11 2005/04/17 14:56:02 daniel Exp $ -->

<chapter id="ipsec"> <?dbhtml filename="ipsec.html"?>
  <title>IPsec</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>Theory</title>

    <para>
      <acronym>IPsec</acronym> is a standard for securing IP communication
      through authentication, and encryption. Besides that it can compress
      packets, reducing traffic.  The following protocols are part of the
      IPsec standard:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <acronym>AH</acronym> (Authentication Header) provides authenticity
          guarantee for transported packets. This is done by checksumming the
          packages using a cryptographic algorithm. If the checksum is found to
          be correct by the receiver, the receiver can be assured that the 
	  packet is not modified, and that the packet really originated from 
	  the reported sender (provided that the keys are only known by the 
	  sender and receiver). 
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <acronym>ESP</acronym> (Encapsulating Security Payload) is used to
          encrypt packets. This makes the data of the packet confident, and
	  only readable by the host with the right decryption key.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <acronym>IPcomp</acronym> (IP payload compression) provides
	  compression before a packet is encrypted. This is useful, because
	  encrypted data generally compresses worse than unencrypted data.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <acronym>IKE</acronym> (Internet Key Exchange) provides the means to
          negotiate keys in secrecy. Please note that IKE is optional, keys can
          be configured manually.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      There are actually two modes of operation: <emphasis>transport
      mode</emphasis> is used to encrypt normal connections between two 
      hosts, <emphasis>tunnel mode</emphasis> encapsulates the original
      package in a new header. In this chapter we are going to look at the 
      transport mode, because the primary goal of this chapter is to show 
      how to set up a secure connection between two hosts.
    </para>

    <para>
      There are also two major methods of authentication. You can use manual
      keys, or an Internet Key Exchange (IKE) daemon, like racoon, that 
      automatically exchanges keys securely betwoon two hosts. In both cases
      you need to set up a policy in the Security Policy Database (SPD). This
      database is used by the kernel to decide what kind of security policy
      is needed to communicate with another host. If you use manual keying you
      also have to set up Security Association Database (SAD) entries, which
      specifies what encryption algorithmn and key should be used for secure
      communication with another host. If you use an IKE daemon the security
      associations are automatically established.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Kernel configuration</title>

    <para>
      Native IPsec support is only available in &Kernel; 2.6.x
      kernels.  Earlier kernels have no native IPsec support. So, make
      sure that you have a 2.6.x kernel. The 2.6 kernel is available
      in &Distribution; 10.0 and 10.1 from the
      <filename>testing</filename> directory on CD2 of the &Distribution; 
      CD sets, or any of the official &Distribution; mirrors.  The
      default &Distribution; 2.6 kernel has support for AH, ESP and IPcomp
      in for both IPv4 and IPv6. If you are compiling a custom kernel
      enable use at least the following options in your kernel
      configuration:
    </para>

    <screen>
CONFIG_INET_AH=y
CONFIG_INET_ESP=y
CONFIG_INET_IPCOMP=y
    </screen>

    <para>
      Or you can compile support for IPsec protocols as a module:
    </para>

    <screen>
CONFIG_INET_AH=m
CONFIG_INET_ESP=m
CONFIG_INET_IPCOMP=m
    </screen>


    <para>
      In this chapter we are only going to use AH and ESP transformations, but
      it is not a bad idea to enable IPComp transformation for further 
      configuration of IPsec.
    </para>

    <para>
      When you choose to compile IPsec support as a module, make sure
      that the required modules are loaded. For example, if you are going
      to use ESP for IPv4 connections, load the <emphasis>esp4</emphasis>
      module.
    </para>

    <para>
      Compile the kernel as usual and boot it.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Installing IPsec-Tools</title>

    <para>
      The next step is to install the
      <ulink url="http://ipsec-tools.sourceforge.net">IPsec-Tools</ulink>.
      These tools are ports of
      the <ulink url="http://www.kame.net">KAME</ulink> IPsec utilities.
      Download the latest sources and unpack, configure and install them:
    </para>

    <screen>
# <command>tar jxf ipsec-tools-x.y.z.tar.bz2</command>
# <command>cd ipsec-tools-x.y.z</command>
# <command>CFLAGS="-O2 -march=i486 -mcpu=i686" \
  ./configure --prefix=/usr \
              --sysconfdir=/etc \
              --localstatedir=/var \
              --enable-hybrid \
              --enable-natt \
              --enable-dpd \
              --enable-frag \
              i486-slackware-linux</command>
# <command>make</command>
# <command>make install</command>
    </screen>

      <para>
        Replace <emphasis>x.y.z</emphasis> with the version of the
	downloaded sources. The most notable flags that we specify
	during the configuration of the sources are:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>--enable-dpd</emphasis>: enables
	    dead peer detection (DPD). DPD is a method for detecting
	    wether any of the hosts for which security associations
	    are set up is unreachable. When this is the case the
	    security associations to that host can be removed.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>--enable-natt</emphasis>: enables NAT traversal
	    (NAT-T). Since NAT alters the IP headers, this causes
	    problems for guaranteeing authenticity of a packet. NAT-T
	    is a method that helps overcoming this problem. Configuring
	    NAT-T is beyond the scope of this article.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Setting up IPsec with manual keying</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <para>
        We will use an example as the guideline for setting up an encrypted
        connection between to hosts. The hosts have the IP addresses 
        <emphasis>&host1ip;</emphasis> and <emphasis>&host2ip;</emphasis>.
        The <quote>transport mode</quote> of operation will be used with
        AH and ESP transformations and manual keys.
      </para>
      
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Writing the configuration file</title>

      <para>
        The first step is to write a configuration file we will name
        <filename>/etc/setkey.conf</filename>. On the first host
        (&host1ip;) the following <filename>/etc/setkey.conf</filename>
        configuration will be used:
      </para>

      <screen>
#!/usr/sbin/setkey -f

# Flush the SAD and SPD
flush;
spdflush;

add 192.168.1.1 192.168.1.169 ah 0x200 -A hmac-md5 
0xa731649644c5dee92cbd9c2e7e188ee6;
add 192.168.1.169 192.168.1.1 ah 0x300 -A hmac-md5 
0x27f6d123d7077b361662fc6e451f65d8;

add 192.168.1.1 192.168.1.169 esp 0x201 -E 3des-cbc 
0x656c8523255ccc23a66c1917aa0cf30991fce83532a4b224;
add 192.168.1.169 192.168.1.1 esp 0x301 -E 3des-cbc
0xc966199f24d095f3990a320d749056401e82b26570320292

spdadd 192.168.1.1 192.168.1.169 any -P out ipsec
           esp/transport//require
           ah/transport//require;

spdadd 192.168.1.169 192.168.1.1 any -P in ipsec
           esp/transport//require
           ah/transport//require;
      </screen>

      <para>
        The first line (a line ends with a <quote>;</quote>) adds a key
        for the header checksumming for packets coming from &host1ip; 
        going to &host2ip;. The second line does the same for packets
        coming from &host2ip; to &host1ip;. The third and the fourth line
        define the keys for the data encryption the same way as the
        first two lines. Finally the <quote>spadd</quote> lines define
        two policies, namely packets going out from &host1ip; to &host2ip;
        should be (require) encoded (esp) and <quote>signed</quote> with
        the authorization header. The second policy is for incoming packets
        and it is the same as outgoing packages.
      </para>

      <para>
        Please be aware that you should not use these keys, but your own
        secretly kept unique keys. You can generate keys using the
        <filename>/dev/random</filename> device:
      </para>

      <screen>
# <command>dd if=/dev/random count=16 bs=1 | xxd -ps</command>
      </screen>

      <para>
        This command uses dd to output 16 bytes from 
        <filename>/dev/random</filename>. Don't forget to add <quote>0x</quote>
        at the beginning of the line in the configuration files. You can use 
        the 16 byte (128 bits) for the hmac-md5 algorithm that is used for AH.
        The 3des-cbc algorithm that is used for ESP in the example should be fed 
        with a 24 byte (192 bits) key. These keys can be generated with:
      </para>

      <screen>
# <command>dd if=/dev/random count=24 bs=1 | xxd -ps</command>
      </screen>  

      <para>
        Make sure that the <filename>/etc/setkey.conf</filename> file can only
        be read by the root user. If normal users can read the keys IPsec
        provides no security at all. You can do this with:
      </para>

      <screen>
# <command>chmod 600 /etc/setkey.conf</command>
      </screen>

      <para>
        The same <filename>/etc/setkey.conf</filename> can be created on the
        &host2ip; host, with inverted <parameter class="command">-P 
        in</parameter> and <parameter class="command">-P out</parameter> options. So, 
        the <filename>/etc/setkey.conf</filename> will look like this:
      </para>

      <screen>
#!/usr/sbin/setkey -f

# Flush the SAD and SPD
flush;
spdflush;

add 192.168.1.1 192.168.1.169 ah 0x200 -A hmac-md5
0xa731649644c5dee92cbd9c2e7e188ee6;
add 192.168.1.169 192.168.1.1 ah 0x300 -A hmac-md5
0x27f6d123d7077b361662fc6e451f65d8;

add 192.168.1.1 192.168.1.169 esp 0x201 -E 3des-cbc
0x656c8523255ccc23a66c1917aa0cf30991fce83532a4b224;
add 192.168.1.169 192.168.1.1 esp 0x301 -E 3des-cbc
0xc966199f24d095f3990a320d749056401e82b26570320292

spdadd 192.168.1.1 192.168.1.169 any -P in ipsec
           esp/transport//require
           ah/transport//require;

spdadd 192.168.1.169 192.168.1.1 any -P out ipsec
           esp/transport//require
           ah/transport//require;
      </screen>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Activating the IPsec configuration</title>

      <para>
        The IPsec configuration can be activated with the 
	<command>setkey</command> command:
      </para>

      <screen>
# <command>setkey -f /etc/setkey.conf</command>
      </screen>

      <para>
        If you want to enable IPsec permanently you can add the following line
        to <filename>/etc/rc.d/rc.local</filename> on both hosts:
      </para>

      <screen>
/usr/sbin/setkey -f /etc/setkey.conf
      </screen>

      <para>
        After configuring IPsec you can test the connection by running
        <command>tcpdump</command> and simultaneously pinging the other
        host. You can see if AH and ESP are actually used in the 
        <command>tcpdump</command> output:
      </para>

      <screen>
# <command>tcpdump -i eth0</command>
tcpdump: listening on eth0
11:29:58.869988 terrapin.taickim.net > 192.168.1.169: AH(spi=0x00000200,seq=0x40f): ESP(spi=0x00000201,seq=0x40f) (DF)
11:29:58.870786 192.168.1.169 > terrapin.taickim.net: AH(spi=0x00000300,seq=0x33d7): ESP(spi=0x00000301,seq=0x33d7)
      </screen>
      
    </sect2>

  </sect1>
  
  <sect1>
    <title>Setting up IPsec with automatic key exchanging</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Introduction</title>
    
      <para>
        The subject of automatical key exchange is already touched shortly
	in the introduction of this chapter. Put simply, IPsec with IKE
	works in the following steps.
      </para>
      
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
	  <para>
	    Some process on the host wants to connect to another host. The
	    kernel checks whether there is a security policy set up for
	    the other host. If there already is a security association
	    corresponding with the policy the connection can be made,
	    and will be authenticated, encrypted and/or compressed as defined
	    in the security association. If there is no security association,
	    the kernel will request a user-land IKE daemon to set up the
	    necessary security association(s).
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    During the first phase of the key exchange the IKE daemon
	    will try to verify the authenticity of the other host. This
	    is usually done with a preshared key or certificate. If
	    the authentication is successful a secure channel is set up
	    between the two hosts, usually called a IKE security
	    association, to continue the key exchange.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    During the second phase of the key exchange the security
	    associations for communication with the other host are set
	    up. This involves choosing the encryption algorithm to be
	    used, and generating keys that are used for encryption
	    of the communication.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    At this point the first step is repeated again, but since
	    there are now security associations the communication can
	    proceed.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      
      <para>
        The racoon IKE daemon is included with the KAME IPsec tools, the
	sections that follow explain how to set up racoon.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Using racoon with a preshared key</title>
      
      <para>
        As usual the first step to set up IPsec is to define security
	policies. In contrast to the manual keying example you should
	not set up security associations, because racoon will make them
	for you. We will use the same host IPs as in the example above.
	The security policy rules look like this:
      </para>

      <screen>
#!/usr/sbin/setkey -f

# Flush the SAD and SPD
flush;
spdflush;

spdadd &host1ip; &host2ip; any -P out ipsec
	esp/transport//require;

spdadd &host2ip; &host1ip; any -P in ipsec
	esp/transport//require;
      </screen>

      <para>
        Cautious souls have probably noticed that AH policies are missing
        in this example. In most situations this is no problem, ESP can
        provide authentication. But you should be aware that the authentication
        is more narrow; it does not protect information outside the ESP
        headers. But it is more efficient than encapsulating ESP packets
        in AH.
      </para>

      <para>
        With the security policies set up you can configure racoon. Since
        the connection-specific information, like the authentication method
        is specified in the phase one configuration. We can use a general
        phase two configuration. It is also possible to make specific
        phase two settings for certain hosts. But generally speaking a
        general configuration will often suffice in simple setups. We
        will also add paths for the preshared key file, and certification
        directory. This is an example of 
        <filename>/etc/racoon/racoon.conf</filename> with the paths
        and a general phase two policy set up:
      </para>

      <screen>
path pre_shared_key "/etc/racoon/psk.txt";
path certificate "/etc/racoon/certs";

sainfo anonymous {
{
	pfs_group 2;
	lifetime time 1 hour;
	encryption_algorithm 3des, blowfish 448, rijndael;
	authentication_algorithm hmac_sha1, hmac_md5;
	compression_algorithm deflate;
}
      </screen>

      <para>
        The <parameter>sainfo</parameter> identifier is used to make a
        block that specifies the settings for security associations. Instead
        of setting this for a specific host, the <parameter>anonymous</parameter>
        parameter is used to specify that these settings should be used
        for all hosts that do not have a specific configuration. The
        <parameter>pfs_group</parameter> specifies which group of
        Diffie-Hellman exponentiations should be used. The different
        groups provide different lengths of base prime numbers that are
        used for the authentication process. Group 2 provides a 1024 bit
        length if you would like to use a greater length, for increased
        security, you can use another group (like 14 for a 2048 bit
        length). The <parameter>encryption_algorithm</parameter> specifies
        which encryption algorithms this host is willing to use for
        ESP encryption. The <parameter>authentication_algorithm</parameter>
        specifies the algorithm to be used for ESP Authentication or
        AH. Finally, the <parameter>compression_algorithm</parameter>
        is used to specify which compression algorithm should be used
        when IPcomp is specified in an association.
      </para>

      <para>
        The next step is to add a phase one configuration for the key
        exchange with the other host to the racoon configuration. For
        example:
      </para>

      <screen>
remote &host2ip; 
{
	exchange_mode aggressive, main;
	my_identifier address;
	proposal {
		encryption_algorithm 3des;
		hash_algorithm sha1;
		authentication_method pre_shared_key;
		dh_group 2;
	}
}
      </screen>

      <para>
        The <parameter>remote</parameter> block specifies a phase one
        configuration. The <parameter>exchange_mode</parameter> is
        used to configure what exchange mode should be used for
        phase. You can specify more than one exchange mode, but the
        first method is used if this host is the initiator of the
        key exchange. The <parameter>my_identifier</parameter> option
        specifies what identifier should be sent to the remote host.
        If this option committed <parameter>address</parameter> is used,
        which sends the IP address as the identifier. The 
        <parameter>proposal</parameter> block specifies parameter that
        will be proposed to the other host during phase one authentication.
        The <parameter>encryption_algorithm</parameter>, and
        <parameter>dh_group</parameter> are explained above. The
        <parameter>hash_algorithm</parameter> option is mandatory, and
        configures the hash algorithm that should be used. This
        can be <parameter>md5</parameter>, or <parameter>sha1</parameter>.
        The <parameter>authentication_method</parameter> is crucial for
        this configuration, as this parameter is used to specify that
        a preshared key should be used, with 
        <parameter>pre_shared_key</parameter>.
      </para>

      <para>
        With racoon set up there is one thing left to do, the preshared
        key has to be added to <filename>/etc/racoon/psk.txt</filename>.
        The syntax is very simple, each line contains a host IP address
        and a key. These parameters are separated with a tab.
        For example:
      </para>

      <screen>
&host2ip;	somekey
      </screen>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Activating the IPsec configuration</title>

      <para>
        At this point the configuration of the security policies and racoon
        is complete, and you can start to test the configuration. It is a
        good idea to start <command>racoon</command> with the
        <parameter class="command">-F</parameter> parameter. This will run
        racoon in the foreground, making it easier to catch error messages.
        To wrap it up:
      </para>

      <screen>
# <command>setkey -f /etc/setkey.conf</command>
# <command>racoon -F</command>
      </screen>

      <para>
        Now that you have added the security policies to the security policy
        database, and started Racoon, you can test your IPsec configuration.
        For instance, you could ping the other host to start with. The
        first time you ping the other host, this will fail:
      </para>

      <screen>
$ <command>ping &host2ip;</command>
connect: Resource temporarily unavailable
      </screen>

      <para>
        The reason for this is that the security associations still
        have to be set up. But the ICMP packet will trigger the key exchange.
        ping will trigger the key exchange. You can see whether the exchange
        was succesful or not by looking at the Racoon log messages in
        <filename>/var/log/messages</filename>, or the racoon output
        if you started racoon in the foreground. A succesful key exhange
        looks like this:
      </para>

      <screen>
 Apr  4 17:14:58 terrapin racoon: INFO: IPsec-SA request for &host2ip; queued due to no phase1 found.
 Apr  4 17:14:58 terrapin racoon: INFO: initiate new phase 1 negotiation: &host1ip;[500]&lt;=&gt;&host2ip;[500] 
 Apr  4 17:14:58 terrapin racoon: INFO: begin Aggressive mode. 
 Apr  4 17:14:58 terrapin racoon: INFO: received Vendor ID: DPD 
 Apr  4 17:14:58 terrapin racoon: NOTIFY: couldn't find the proper pskey, try to get one by the peer's address.
 Apr  4 17:14:58 terrapin racoon: INFO: ISAKMP-SA established &host1ip;[500]-&host2ip;[500] spi:58c4669f762abf10:60593eb9e3dd7406
 Apr  4 17:14:59 terrapin racoon: INFO: initiate new phase 2 negotiation: &host1ip;[0]&lt;=&gt;&host2ip;[0] 
 Apr  4 17:14:59 terrapin racoon: INFO: IPsec-SA established: ESP/Transport &host2ip;-&gt;host1ip; spi=232781799(0xddff7e7) 
 Apr  4 17:14:59 terrapin racoon: INFO: IPsec-SA established: ESP/Transport &host1ip;-&gt;&host2ip; spi=93933800(0x59950e8) 
      </screen>

      <para>
        After the key exchange, you
        can verify that IPsec is set up correctly by analyzing the packets
        that go in and out with <command>tcpdump</command>. tcpdump is
        available in the <emphasis>n</emphasis> diskset. Suppose that
        the outgoing connection to the other host goes through the
        <emphasis>eth0</emphasis> interface, you can analyze the packats
        that go though the <emphasis>eth0</emphasis> interface with
        <command>tcpdump -i eth0</command>. If the outgoing packets are
        encrypted with ESP, you can see this in the <command>tcpdump</command>
        output. For example:
      </para>

      <screen>
# <command>tcpdump -i eth0</command>
tcpdump: verbose output suppressed, use -v or -vv for full protocol decode
listening on eth0, link-type EN10MB (Ethernet), capture size 96 bytes
17:27:50.241067 IP terrapin.taickim.net &gt; &host2ip;: ESP(spi=0x059950e8,seq=0x9)
17:27:50.241221 IP &host2ip; &gt; terrapin.taickim.net: ESP(spi=0x0ddff7e7,seq=0x9)
      </screen>

    </sect2>
    
  </sect1>

</chapter>
