<!-- $Id: mutt.xml,v 1.1 2005/05/04 07:22:35 daniel Exp $ -->

<chapter id="email-mutt"> <?dbhtml filename="mutt.html"?>
  <title>Reading and writing e-mail with mutt</title>

  <indexterm><primary>mutt</primary></indexterm>

  <sect1 id="email-mutt-introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <indexterm><primary>MUA</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>Mail User Agent</primary></indexterm>

    <para>
      Mutt is a mail user agent (<acronym>MUA</acronym>) that can be used
      for reading and writing e-mail. Mutt is a text-mode installation,
      meaning that it can be used on the console, over SSH and in an X
      terminal. Due to its menu interface, it is very easy to read large
      amounts of e-mail in a short time, and mutt can be configured to
      use your favorite text editor.
    </para>

    <para>
      This chapter will discuss how you can customize mutt for your needs,
      how to use it, and how PGP/GnuPG support is used.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="email-mutt-basicsetup">
    <title>Basic setup</title>

    <para>
      There are a few mutt settings you often want to configure. This section
      describes these settings. User-specific mutt customizations can be made
      in the <filename>.muttrc</filename> in the user's home directory. You
      can change global mutt settings in <filename>/etc/mutt/Muttrc</filename>.
    </para>

    <sect2 id="email-mutt-basicsetup-headers">
      <title>Customized headers</title>

      <indexterm><primary>mutt</primary><secondary>headers</secondary></indexterm>

      <para>
        Each e-mail has headers with various information. For example, the
        header contains information about the path an e-mail has traversed
        after it has been sent. The sender (<emphasis>From:</emphasis>) and
        recipient (<emphasis>To:</emphasis>) e-mail addresses are also stored
        in the headers, as well as the subject (<emphasis>Subject:</emphasis>)
        of an e-mail. You can add your own headers to an e-mail with the
        <emphasis>my_hdr</emphasis> configuration option. This option
        has the following syntax: <emphasis>my_hdr &lt;header name&gt;:
        &lt;header contents&gt;</emphasis>. For example, you can add information
        about what OS you are running by adding the following line to your
        mutt configuration:
      </para>

      <screen>
my_hdr X-Operating-System: &Distribution; 10.1
      </screen>

      <para>
        You can also override some of the headers that are normally used,
        such as the sender address that is specified in the
        <emphasis>From:</emphasis> header:
      </para>

      <screen>
my_hdr From: John Doe &lt;john.doe@example.org&gt;
      </screen>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>The sendmail binary</title>

      <indexterm><primary>mutt</primary><secondary>sendmail binary</secondary></indexterm>

      <para>
        By default mutt uses the sendmail MTA to deliver e-mails that
        were sent. You can use another command to send e-mail by altering
        the <emphasis>sendmail</emphasis> configuration variable. The
        sendmail replacement must handle the same parameter syntax
        as sendmail. For example, if you have installed MSMTP to deliver
        e-mails, you can configure mutt to use it by adding the following
        line to your mutt configuration:
      </para>

      <screen>
set sendmail="/usr/bin/msmtp"
      </screen>

      <para>
        When you have completely replaced sendmail with another MTA, for
        instance Postfix, it is usually not needed to set this parameter,
        because most MTAs provide an alternative sendmail binary file.
      </para>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>

</chapter>
