<!-- $Id: proc.xml,v 1.2 2004/11/28 18:53:43 daniel Exp $ -->

<chapter id="chap-proc"> <?dbhtml filename="proc.html"?>
<title>Process management</title>

<sect1>
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
Unix-like operating systems work with processes. A process is an unit
the operating system schedules for CPU time and the memory manager manages
memory for. Basically a process consists of program code (named text), 
data (used by a program) and a stack. The stack is used by the program
to store variables. Programs are at least one process. A program/process
can ask the system to create a new copy of itself, which is called a
fork. For example, a web server could fork itself to let the new process
handle a request.
</para>

<para>
A process can be parted in threads. The difference between forking a
process and creating a thread is that different threads share the address 
space of the process. A forked process is a separate process with its own
address space. Forking is more expensive in terms of memory requirement
and CPU time. 
</para>

<para>
A user can control a process by sending signals to the process. For example,
the SIGTERM command is used to terminate a process, and the SIGHUP signal
to restart a process.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Process basics</title>

<para>
This section describes some basic commands that are used for process
management.
</para>

<sect2>
<title>ps</title>

<para>
The <command>ps</command>(1) command is used to report which processes
are currently active. By running <command>ps</command> without any
parameters you can see which processes are active in the current user
session. Let's look at an example:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>ps</command>
  PID TTY          TIME CMD
 1191 pts/2    00:00:00 bash
 1216 pts/2    00:00:00 ps
</screen>  

<para>
In this example the <command>bash</command> and <command>ps</command>
commands are running. As you can see each process has a process ID
(PID). You will need the process number if you want to send a signal
to a process, for example a kill signal. The <command>ps</command>
has many parameters to modify the output. For example, the 
<varname>x</varname> shows all processes without a controlling tty:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>ps x</command>
  PID TTY      STAT   TIME COMMAND
 1044 tty1     S      0:00 -bash
 1089 tty1     S      0:00 /bin/sh /usr/X11R6/bin/startx
 1100 tty1     S      0:00 xinit /home/daniel/.xinitrc --
 1108 tty1     S      0:00 /usr/bin/wmaker
 1113 tty1     S      0:00 sylpheed
 1114 tty1     S      0:00 /bin/sh /opt/firefox/run-mozilla.sh /opt/firefox/fire
 1120 tty1     S      0:52 /opt/firefox/firefox-bin
 1125 tty1     S      0:00 /usr/libexec/gconfd-2 20
 1146 tty1     S      0:00 xchat
 1161 tty1     S      0:00 xterm -sb
 1163 pts/0    S      0:00 bash
 1170 pts/0    S      0:00 vi proc.xml
 1189 tty1     S      0:00 xterm -sb
 1191 pts/2    S      0:00 bash
 1275 pts/2    R      0:00 ps x
</screen>

<para>
Have a look at the <command>ps</command>(1) manual page for a summary
of available parameters.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>kill</title>

<para>
The <command>kill</command>(1) sends a signal to a process. If no signal is
specified the TERM signal is send, which asks a process to exit gracefully.
Let's have a look at the normal mode of execution:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>ps ax | grep mc</command>
 1045 tty4     S      0:00 /usr/bin/mc -P /tmp/mc-daniel/mc.pwd.756
$ <command>kill 1045</command>
$ <command>ps ax | grep mc</command>
$
</screen>

<para>
As you can see the <command>ps</command> is used to look for the 
<command>mc</command> process. There is one occurrence of <command>mc</command>
running with PID 1045. This process is killed, and the second 
<command>ps</command> command shows that the process is indeed terminated.
</para>

<para>
As we said earlier the <command>kill</command> command can also be used to
send other signals. The <command>kill -l</command> displays a list of signals
that can be sent:
</para>

<screen>
 1) SIGHUP       2) SIGINT       3) SIGQUIT      4) SIGILL
 5) SIGTRAP      6) SIGABRT      7) SIGBUS       8) SIGFPE
 9) SIGKILL     10) SIGUSR1     11) SIGSEGV     12) SIGUSR2
13) SIGPIPE     14) SIGALRM     15) SIGTERM     17) SIGCHLD
18) SIGCONT     19) SIGSTOP     20) SIGTSTP     21) SIGTTIN
22) SIGTTOU     23) SIGURG      24) SIGXCPU     25) SIGXFSZ
26) SIGVTALRM   27) SIGPROF     28) SIGWINCH    29) SIGIO
30) SIGPWR      31) SIGSYS
</screen>

<para>
The SIGKILL signal is often used to kill processes that refuse to terminate
with the default SIGTERM signal. The signal can be specified by using the
number as a parameter, for example, the following command would send a SIGKILL
signal to PID 1045:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>kill -9 1045</command>
</screen>

<para>
It is also possible to specify the signal without the <quote>SIG</quote>
letters as a parameter. In the following example the SIGHUP signal is sent
to the <command>inetd</command> to restart it:
</para>

<screen>
# <command>ps ax | grep inetd</command>
  727 ?        S      0:00 /usr/sbin/inetd
# <command>kill -HUP 727</command>
</screen>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<!-- XXX - Come up with something better -->
<title>Advanced process management</title>

<sect2>
<title>Background processes</title>

<para>
Normally a process takes over the screen and keyboard after it is started.
It is also possible to start processes as a background process, this means
that the shell starts the process, but keeps control over the terminal.
In most shells a process can be started as a background process by placing
an ampersand (&amp;) after the command. For example:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>rm -rf ~/bunch/of/files &amp;</command>
</screen>

<para>
A process that runs in the background can be brought to the foreground using
the <command>fg %&lt;job ID&gt;</command> command. You can see which
jobs are running, with their job numbers, using the <command>jobs</command>
command. For example:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>sleep 1000 &amp;</command>
[1] 947
$ <command>jobs</command>
[1]+  Running                 sleep 1000 &amp;
$ <command>fg %1</command>
sleep 1000
</screen>

<para>
The first command, <command>sleep 1000 &amp;</command>, starts sleep in the 
background. <command>sleep</command> is a command does nothing but waiting
the number of seconds that are specified as a parameter. The output of
the <command>jobs</command> command shows that <command>sleep</command>
is indeed running, with Job ID <emphasis>1</emphasis>. Finally we move
<command>sleep</command> to the foreground. As you can see, the shell will
print which command is moved to the foreground.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Stopping processes</title>
<para>
A process that is running can be stopped by pressing
the &lt;Control&gt; and &lt;z&gt; keys simultaneously. Stopped processes
can be moved to the foreground with the <command>fg</command> command. Running
<command>fg</command> without any parameters moves the last process that was
stopped to the foreground. Other processes can be moved
to the foreground by specifying the job ID as a parameter to
<command>fg</command>.
</para>

<para>
A stopped process can also be told to continue as a background process,
by executing <command>bg &lt;job ID&gt;</command>. Executing 
<command>fg</command> without any parameter will move the last stopped process 
to the background.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Altering priorities</title>

<para>
The Linux kernel allows a user to change the priority of a program. For
example, suppose that you want to run a process that requires a lot of CPU
time, but you do not want to hinder other users. In this
case you can start the process with a low priority, the process will
only get CPU time when there are not many other processes demanding
CPU time. Or you can give processes that are important a higher priority.
</para>

<para>
GNU/Linux provides two commands to alter the priority of a process. The
<command>nice</command>(1) command can be used to specify the priority when
you are launching a process. With the <command>renice</command>(1) command
you can alter the priority of a process that is already running. The priority
is a numerical value from -20 (highest priority) to 19 (lowest priority).
Let's start with an example of <command>nice</command> in action:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>nice -n 19 ./setiathome</command>
</screen>

<para>
As you can see the <emphasis>-n</emphasis> parameter is used to specify
the priority value. In this case the <command>./setiathome</command> will
have a very low priority. Be aware that only the superuser can use negative
priority values. Thus, a normal user cannot give a process a higher priority,
as illustrated by this example:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>nice -n -1 nice</command>
nice: cannot set priority: Permission denied
</screen>

<para>
But it will work as the <emphasis>root</emphasis> user:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>su -c "nice -n -1 nice"</command>
Password: 
-1
</screen>

<para>
The <command>renice</command> command has a somewhat different syntax.
The easiest way to use it is to specify the new priority and the process
ID as parameters to the <command>renice</command> command, as is 
shown in the following example:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>renice +5 5811</command>
5811: old priority 0, new priority 5
</screen>

<para>
As with <command>nice</command> a non-<emphasis>root</emphasis> user
cannot set negative priority values:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>renice -5 5811</command>
renice: 5811: setpriority: Permission denied
</screen>

<note>
<para>
A normal user can not increase the priority of the process beyond the
default priority of 0. Such facilities could be misused by careless
users. After all, the command <command>nice</command> is derived from
being nice to the other users on the system ;^).
</para>
</note>

</sect2>
</sect1>


</chapter>
