<!-- $Id: security.xml,v 1.3 2004/12/18 22:14:34 daniel Exp $ -->

<chapter> <?dbhtml filename="security.html"?>
<title>Security</title>

<sect1>
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
With the increasing usage of the Internet and wireless networks security
is getting more important every day. It is impossible to cover this subject
in a single chapter of an introduction to &OS;. This chapter covers
some basic security techniques that provide a good start for desktop
and server security.
</para>

<para>
Before we go on to specific subjects, it is a good idea to make some remarks
about passwords. Computer authorization largely relies on passwords. Be
sure to use good passwords in all situations. Avoid using words, names,
birth dates and short passwords. These passwords can easily be cracked
with dictionary attacks or brute force attacks against hosts or password
hashes. Use long passwords, ideally eight characters or longer, consisting
of random letters (including capitals) and numbers.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>E-Mail security</title>

<sect2>
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
&OS; supports two major of securing e-mails, but before we will look
into these specifically we are going to look what e-mail security provides.
There are two ways in which you can secure e-mails: signing e-mail and
encrypting e-mail. Signing e-mail means that a special digital signature
is added to the e-mail by the mail user agent. The recipient can use the
signature to check whether an e-mail is really from the sender it claims
to be from or not, and that the message is not in any way changed during
the transmission. E-Mail encryption codes the e-mail in a way that
only the intended recipient can decode it.
</para>

<para>
This system relies on two keys: the private and the public key. Public
keys are used to encrypt messages, and messages can only be decrypted
with the private key. This means that one can sent his public key out to
people. People can use this key to send encrypted e-mails, that only 
the person with the private key can decode. Of course, this means that
the security of this system depends on how well the private is kept
secret.
</para>

<para>
One might wonder why he or she should use one of these techniques. While
most people do not feel the need to encrypt most of their e-mails, it
generally is a good idea to sign your e-mails. There are, for example,
a lot of viruses these days that use other people's e-mail addresses
in the <emphasis>From:</emphasis> field of viruses. If the people who
you are communicating with know that you sign your e-mails, they will
not open fake e-mail from viruses. Besides that it looks much more
professional if people can check your identity, especially in business
transactions. For example, who would you rather trust, 
<emphasis>vampire_boy93853@hotmail.com</emphasis>, or someone using
a professional e-mail address with digitally signed e-mails?
</para>

<bridgehead>GnuPG or S/MIME</bridgehead>

<para>
At the moment there two major standards that are supported by &OS;,
the OpenPGP standard, by the GnuPG tool, and S/MIME. Both are about
equally good concerning the strength of the used encryption algorithms.
The big difference is that S/MIME relies on a certificate authority
(CA), GnuPG does not. A certificate authority is an organization that
is authorized to hand out keys. This means that the certificate authority
validates that the e-mail address and/or name in the certificate is
authentic. This means that either:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
The certificate (aka private and public key) belongs to the owner of
the e-mail address. E-Mail verification is used by the certificate
authority to check this.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
The certificate belongs to the owner of the e-mail address, and to the
name in the certificate. This involves an extra step than e-mail verification.
To have a certificate with a name, your identity has to be checked by
the certificate authority.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
As you can see this system is quite bullet-proof, and you can reasonably
expect that a certificate is authentically representing the e-mail address
and/or person. GnuPG does not use a certificate authority. This means that
anybody can make a key with your name and e-mail address. Trust is established
by signing keys. For example, person A verifies that person B's key really
belongs to person B, by meeting him in real life, and he signs his key. The
authenticity of a key is more certain if it is signed by people who you
trust. As you can guess this system is not completely bullet proof, and it
can take some time to get your key trusted by other people. Besides, if
you use another e-mail address, ant want to use a new key you will have to
start all over again. The advantage of this approach is that your private
key is not known to a certificate authority.
</para>

<para>
GnuPG used to be supported a lot better on &OS;, but more and more
e-mail clients support S/MIME these days. On Windows S/MIME is better
supported, because Outlook Express and Mozilla Mail (two commonly used
e-mail clients) both have S/MIME support. If you are communicating
with many people that use Windows, it is a good choice to go for S/MIME,
because it is worthless to use signed e-mails if the recipient can not
verify them by default.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Configuring and using GnuPG</title>

<para>
This section gives a short introduction on how to configure and use
GnuPG. Make sure you have GnuPG installed. If you have not, you can
install it from the <quote>n</quote> diskset.
</para>

<sect3>
<title>Generating your private and public keys</title>

<para>
Generating public and private keys is a bit complicated, because GnuPG
uses DSA keys by default. DSA is an encryption algorithm, the problem is
that the maximum key length of DSA is 1024 bits, this is considered too
short for the longer term. That is why it is a good idea to use 2048 bit
RSA keys. This section describers how this can be done.
</para>

<note>
<para>
1024-bit keys were believed to be secure for a long time. But Bernstein's
paper "Circuits for Integer Factorization: a Proposal" contests this, the
bottom line is that it is quite feasible for national security agencies to
produce hardware that can break keys in a relatively short amount of time.
Besides that it has be shown that 512-bit RSA keys can be broken in a 
relatively short time using common hardware. More information about these
issues can by found in this e-mail to the cypherpunks list:
<ulink url="http://lists.saigon.com/vault/security/encryption/rsa1024.html" />
</para>
</note>

<para>
We can generate a key by executing:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>gpg --gen-key</command>
</screen>

<para>
The first question is what kind of key you would like to make. We will
choose <emphasis>(4) RSA (sign only)</emphasis>:
</para>

<screen>
Please select what kind of key you want:
   (1) DSA and ElGamal (default)
   (2) DSA (sign only)
   (4) RSA (sign only)
Your selection? <command>4</command>
</screen>

<para>
You will then be asked what the size of the key you want to generate has
to be. Type in <emphasis>2048</emphasis> to generate a 2048 bit key, and
press enter to continue.
</para>

<screen>
What keysize do you want? (1024) <command>2048</command>
</screen>

<para>
The next question is simple to answer, just choose what you like. Generally
speaking it is not a bad idea to let the key be valid infinitely. You can
always deactivate the key with a special revocation certificate.
</para>

<screen>
Please specify how long the key should be valid.
         0 = key does not expire
      &lt;n&gt;  = key expires in n days
      &lt;n&gt;w = key expires in n weeks
      &lt;n&gt;m = key expires in n months
      &lt;n&gt;y = key expires in n years
Key is valid for? (0) <command>0</command>
</screen>

<para>
GnuPG will then ask for confirmation. After confirming your name and e-mail
address will be requested. GnuPG will also ask for a comment, you can leave
this blank, or you could fill in something like <quote>Work</quote> or
<quote>Private</quote>, to indicate what the key is used for. For example:
</para>

<screen>
Real name: <command>John Doe</command>
Email address: <command>john@doe.com</command>
Comment: <command>Work</command>              
You selected this USER-ID:
    "John Doe (Work) &lt;john@doe.com&gt;"
</screen>

<para>
GnuPG will the ask you to confirm your user ID. After confirming it GnuPG
will ask you to enter a password. Be sure to use a good password:
</para>

<screen>
You need a Passphrase to protect your secret key.    

Enter passphrase:
</screen>

<para>
After entering the password twice GnuPG will generate the keys. But we are
not done yet. GnuPG has only generated a key for signing information, not
for encryption of information. To continue, have a look at the output,
and look for the key ID. In the information about the key you will see
<emphasis>pub  2048R/</emphasis>. The key ID is printed after this fragment.
In this example:
</para>

<screen>
public and secret key created and signed.
key marked as ultimately trusted.

pub  2048R/8D080768 2004-07-16 John Doe (Work) &lt;john@doe.com&gt;
     Key fingerprint = 625A 269A 16B9 C652 B953  8B64 389A E0C9 8D08 0768
</screen>

<para>
the key ID is <emphasis>8D080768</emphasis>. If you lost the output of the
key generation you can still find the key ID in the output of the
<command>gpg --list-keys</command> command. Use the key ID to tell GnuPG
that you want to edit your key:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>gpg --edit-key &lt;Key ID&gt;</command>
</screen>

<para>
With the example key above the command would be:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>gpg --edit-key 8D080768</command>
</screen>

<para>
GnuPG will now display a command prompt. Execute the <command>addkey</command>
command on this command prompt:
</para>

<screen>
Command&gt; <command>addkey</command>
</screen>

<para>
GnuPG will now ask the password you used for your key:
</para>

<screen>
Key is protected.

You need a passphrase to unlock the secret key for
user: "John Doe (Work) &lt;john@doe.com&gt;"
2048-bit RSA key, ID 8D080768, created 2004-07-16

Enter passphrase:
</screen>

<para>
After entering the password GnuPG will ask you what kind of key you
would like to create. Choose <emphasis>RSA (encrypt only)</emphasis>, and fill
in the information like you did earlier (be sure to use a 2048 bit key). 
For example:
</para>

<screen>
Please select what kind of key you want:
   (2) DSA (sign only)
   (3) ElGamal (encrypt only)
   (4) RSA (sign only)
   (5) RSA (encrypt only)
Your selection? <command>5</command>
What keysize do you want? (1024) <command>2048</command>
Requested keysize is 2048 bits       
Please specify how long the key should be valid.
         0 = key does not expire
      &lt;n&gt;  = key expires in n days
      &lt;n&gt;w = key expires in n weeks
      &lt;n&gt;m = key expires in n months
      &lt;n&gt;y = key expires in n years
Key is valid for? (0) <command>0</command>
</screen>

<para>
And confirm that the information is correct. After the key is generated
you can leave the GnuPG command prompt, and save the new key with the
<command>save</command> command:
</para>

<screen>
Command&gt; <command>save</command>
</screen>

<para>
Congratulations! You have now generated the necessary keys to encrypt
and decrypt e-mails and files. You can now configure your e-mail client
to use GnuPG. It is a good idea to store the contents of the
<filename>.gnupg</filename> directory on some reliable medium, and store that
in a safe place! If your private key is lost you can't decrypt files and 
messages that were encrypted with your public key. If the private key, and your
password are stolen, the security of this system is completely compromised.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Exporting your public key</title>

<para>
To make GnuPG useful, you have to give your public key to people who send
you files or e-mails. They can use your public key to encrypt files, or use
it to verify whether a file has a correct signature or not. The key can
be exported using the <emphasis>--export</emphasis> parameter. It is also
a good idea to specify the <emphasis>--output</emphasis> parameter, this
will save the key in a file. The following command would save the public
key of <emphasis>John Doe</emphasis>, used in earlier examples, to
the file <filename>key.gpg</filename>:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>gpg --output key.gpg --export john@doe.com</command>
</screen>

<para>
This saves the key in binary format. Often it is more convenient to
use the so-called <quote>ASCII armored output</quote>, which fits better 
for adding the key to e-mails, or websites. You export an ASCII armored
version of the key by adding the <emphasis>--armor</emphasis> parameter:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>gpg --armor --output key.gpg --export john@doe.com</command>
</screen>

<para>
If you look at the <filename>key.gpg</filename> file you will notice that
the ASCII armored key is a much more comfortable format.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Signatures</title>

<para>
With GPG you can make a signature for a file. This signature is unique,
because your signature can only be made with your private key. This means
that other people can check whether the file was really sent by you, and
whether it was in any way altered or not. Files can be signed with the
<emphasis>--detach-sign</emphasis> parameter. Let us look at an example. This 
command will make a signature for the <filename>memo.txt</filename> file. The 
signature will be stored in <filename>memo.txt.sig</filename>.
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>gpg --output memo.txt.sig --detach-sign memo.txt</command>

You need a passphrase to unlock the secret key for
user: "John Doe (Work) &lt;john@doe.com&gt;"
2048-bit RSA key, ID 8D080768, created 2004-07-16

Enter passphrase:
</screen>

<para>
As you can see, GnuPG will ask you to enter the password for your
private key. After you have entered the right key the signature file
(<filename>memo.txt.sig</filename>) will be created.
</para>

<para>
You can verify a file with its signature using the 
<emphasis>--verify</emphasis> parameter. Specify the signature file
as a parameter to the <emphasis>--verify parameter</emphasis>. The
file that needs to be verified can be specified as the final parameter:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command> gpg --verify memo.txt.sig memo.txt</command>
gpg: Signature made Tue Jul 20 23:47:45 2004 CEST using RSA key ID 8D080768
gpg: Good signature from "John Doe (Work) &lt;john@doe.com&gt;"
</screen>

<para>
This will confirm that the file was indeed signed by <emphasis>John Doe (Work) 
&lt;john@doe.com&gt;</emphasis>, with the key <emphasis>8D080768</emphasis>,
and that the file is unchanged. Suppose the file was changed, GnuPG would
have complained about it loudly:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>gpg --verify memo.txt.sig memo.txt</command>
gpg: Signature made Tue Jul 20 23:47:45 2004 CEST using RSA key ID 8D080768
gpg: BAD signature from "John Doe (Work) &lt;john@doe.com&gt;"
</screen>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Closing services</title>

<sect2>
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
Many &OS; run some services that are open to a local network or the
Internet. Other hosts can connect to these services by connecting to specific
ports. For example, port 80 is used for WWW traffic. The
<filename>/etc/services</filename> file contains a table with all commonly
used services, and the port numbers that are used for these services.
</para>

<para>
A secure system should only run the services that are necessary. So, suppose
that a host is acting as a web server, it should not have ports open (thus
servicing) FTP or SMTP. With more open ports security risks increase very
fast, because there is a bigger chance that the software servicing a port
has a vulnerability, or is badly configured. The following few sections
will help you tracking down which ports are open, and closing them.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Finding open ports</title>

<para>
Open ports can be found using a port scanner. Probably the most famous 
port scanner for &OS; is <command>nmap</command>. <command>nmap</command>
is available through the <quote>n</quote> diskset. 
</para>

<para>
The basic <command>nmap</command> syntax is: <command>nmap host</command>. The
<emphasis>host</emphasis> parameter can either be a hostname or IP address.
Suppose that we would like to scan the host that <command>nmap</command>
is installed on. In this case we could specify the 
<emphasis>localhost</emphasis> IP address, <emphasis>127.0.0.1</emphasis>:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>nmap 127.0.0.1</command>

Starting nmap V. 3.00 ( www.insecure.org/nmap/ )
Interesting ports on localhost (127.0.0.1):
(The 1596 ports scanned but not shown below are in state: closed)
Port       State       Service
21/tcp     open        ftp                     
22/tcp     open        ssh                     
23/tcp     open        telnet                  
80/tcp     open        http                    
6000/tcp   open        X11                     

Nmap run completed -- 1 IP address (1 host up) scanned in 0 seconds
</screen>

<para>
In this example you can see that the host has five open ports that are
being serviced; ftp, ssh, telnet, http and X11.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>inetd</title>

<para>
There are two ways to offer TCP/IP services: by running server
applications  stand-alone as a daemon or by using the internet super
server, <command>inetd</command>(8). inetd  is a daemon which monitors
a range of ports. If a client attempts to connect  to a port inetd
handles the connection and forwards the connection to the  server
software which handles that kind of connection. The advantage of this
approach is that it adds an extra layer of security and it makes it
easier to  log incoming connections. The disadvantage is that it is
somewhat slower than  using a stand-alone daemon. It is thus a good
idea to run a stand-alone daemon on, for example, a heavily loaded FTP
server.
</para>

<para>
You can check whether <command>inetd</command> is running on a host or
not with <command>ps</command>, for example:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>ps ax | grep inetd</command>
 2845 ?        S      0:00 /usr/sbin/inetd
</screen>

<para>
In this example inetd is running with PID (process ID) 2845. 
<command>inetd</command> can be configured using the
<filename>/etc/inetd.conf</filename> file. Let's have a look at an example 
line from inetd.conf:
</para>

<screen>
# File Transfer Protocol (FTP) server:
ftp     stream  tcp     nowait  root    /usr/sbin/tcpd  proftpd
</screen>

<para>
This line specifies that inetd should accept FTP connections and pass them to 
<command>tcpd</command>. This may seem a bit odd, because 
<command>proftpd</command> normally handles FTP connections. You can also 
specify to use proftpd directly in <filename>inetd.conf</filename>, but 
it is a good idea to give the connection to <command>tcpd</command>. This 
program passes the connection to <command>proftpd</command> in turn, as 
specified. <command>tcpd</command> is used to monitor services and to provide 
host based access control. 
</para>

<para>
Services can be disabled by adding the comment character (#) at the beginning 
of the line. It is a good idea to disable all services and enable services you 
need one at a time. After changing <filename>/etc/inetd.conf</filename> 
<command>inetd</command> needs to be restarted to activate the changes. This 
can be done by sending the HUP signal to the inetd process:
</para>

<screen>
# <command>ps ax | grep 'inetd'</command>
   2845 ?        S      0:00 /usr/sbin/inetd
# <command>kill -HUP 2845</command>
</screen>

<para>
If you do not need <command>inetd</command> at all, it is a good idea to
remove it. If you want to keep it installed, but do not want &Distribution;
to load it at the booting process, execute the following command as root:
</para>

<screen>
# <command>chmod a-x /etc/rc.d/rc.inetd</command>
</screen>
</sect2>
</sect1>

</chapter>
