<!-- $Id: shell.xml,v 1.2 2004/11/28 18:53:43 daniel Exp $ -->

<chapter> <?dbhtml filename="shell.html"?>
<title>The Bash shell</title>

<sect1>
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
The shell is the traditional interface used by UNIX and GNU/Linux. In contrast
to the X Window System it is an interface that works with commands. In the
beginning this can be a bit awkward, but the shell is very powerful. Even
in these days the shell is almost unavoidable ;).
</para>

<para>
The default shell on Slackware GNU/Linux is Bash. Bash means <quote>Bourne-Again
SHell</quote>, which is a pun on the name of one of the traditional UNIX shells,
the <quote>Bourne Shell</quote>. Slackware also provides some other shells, but
Bash is the main topic of this chapter.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Starting the shell</title>

<para>
The procedure for starting the shell depends on whether you use a graphical
or text-mode login. If you are logging on in text-mode the shell is 
immediately started after entering the (correct) password. If you are using
a graphical login manager like gdm, log on as you would normally, and look in 
your window manager or desktop environment menu for an entry named "XTerm".
XTerm is a terminal emulator, after the terminal emulator is started the
shell comes up.
</para>

<para>
The shell might remind some people of MS-DOS. Be happy, it has nothing to
do with DOS, the only similarity is that you can enter commands ;).
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Shell basics</title>

<para>
This chapter might be a difficult to read for the first time, because
you might not know any shell commands. Many important commands are
described in the next chapters, but those chapters are not really useful
without any knowledge of the shell. So, it is not a bad idea to
browse quickly through this chapter, and the next few chapters, to get
an idea what this shell thing is all about. After that quick overview
you should be able to understand this chapter.
</para>

<sect2>
<title>Executing commands</title>

<para>
The most important job for the shell is to execute your commands. Let's
look at a simple example. Most UNIX variants have a command named
<command>whoami</command>, which shows as which user you are logged in.
Try typing <command>whoami</command>, and press the &lt;Enter&gt;
after that. The &lt;Enter&gt; tells the shell that it should execute
the command that you have typed on the current line. The output looks
like this:
</para>

<screen>
daniel@tazzy:~$ <command>whoami</command>
daniel
daniel@tazzy:~$
</screen>

<para>
As you can see the control is handed back to the shell after the command
is finished.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Browsing through shell commands</title>

<para>
It often happens that you have to execute commands that you executed earlier.
Fortunately, you do not have to type them all over again. You can browse
through the history of executed commands with the up and down arrows. Besides
that it is also possible to search for a command. Press &lt;Control&gt; +
&lt;r&gt; and start typing the command you want to execute. You will notice
that bash will display the first match it can find. If this is not the
match you were looking for you can continue typing the command (till it
is unique and a match appears), or press &lt;Control&gt; + &lt;r&gt;
once more to get the next match. When you have found the command you were
looking for, you can execute it by pressing &lt;Enter&gt;.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Completion</title>

<para>
Completion is one of the most useful functionalities of Unix-like shells.
Suppose that you have a directory with two files named 
<filename>websites</filename> and <filename>recipe</filename>. And suppose
you want to <command>cat</command> the file <filename>websites</filename>
(<command>cat</command> shows the contents of a file), by specifying
<filename>websites</filename> as a parameter to cat. Normally you would
type <quote>cat websites</quote>, and execute the command. Try typing
<quote>cat w</quote>, and hit the &lt;Tab&gt; key. Bash will automatically
expand what you typed to <quote>cat websites</quote>.
</para>

<para>
But what happens if you have files that start with the same letter? Suppose
that you have the <filename>recipe1.txt</filename> and 
<filename>recipe2.txt</filename> files. Type <quote>cat r</quote> 
and hit &lt;Tab&gt;, Bash will complete the filename as far as it can. It 
would leave you with <quote>cat recipe</quote>. Try hitting &lt;Tab&gt;
again, and Bash will show you a list of filenames that start with
<quote>recipe</quote>, in this case both recipe files. At this point you
have to help Bash by typing the next character of the file you need.
Suppose you want to <command>cat</command> <filename>recipe2</filename>,
you can push the &lt;2&gt; key. After that there are no problems completing
the filename, and hitting &lt;Tab&gt; completes the command to
<quote>cat recipe2.txt</quote>.
</para>

<para>
It is worth noting that completion also works with commands. Most GNU/Linux
commands are quite short, so it will not be of much use most of the time.
</para>

<para>
It is a good idea to practice a bit with completion, it can save alot
of keystrokes if you can handle completion well. You can make some
empty files to practive with using the <command>touch</command> command.
For example, to make a file named <filename>recipe3.txt</filename>,
execute <command>touch recipe3.txt</command>.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Wildcards</title>

<para>
Most shells, including Bash, support wildcards. Wildcards are special
characters that can be used to do pattern matching. The table listed
below displays some commonly used wildcards. We are going to look at
several examples to give a general idea how wildcards work.
</para>

<table><title>Bash wildcards</title>
<tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
<thead>
<row>
  <entry>Wildcard</entry>
  <entry>Matches</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>*</entry>
<entry>A string of characters</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>?</entry>
<entry>A single character</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>[]</entry>
<entry>A character in an array of characters</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

<sect3>
<title>Matching a string of characters</title>

<para>
As you can see in the table above the <quote>*</quote> character matches
a string of characters. For example, <emphasis>*.html</emphasis> matches
everything ending with <emphasis>.html</emphasis>, <emphasis>d*.html</emphasis>
matches everything starting with a <emphasis>d</emphasis> and ending with
<emphasis>.html</emphasis>.
</para>

<para>
Suppose that you would like to list all files in the current directory with
the <emphasis>.html</emphasis> extension, the following command will do the
job:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>ls *.html</command>
book.html        installation.html     pkgmgmt.html  usermgmt.html
filesystem.html  internet.html         printer.html  xfree86.html
gfdl.html        introduction.html     proc.html
help.html        slackware-basics.html shell.html
</screen>

<para>
Likewise we could remove all files starting with an <emphasis>in</emphasis>:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>rm in*</command>
</screen>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Matching single characters</title>

<para>
The <quote>?</quote> wildcard works as the <quote>*</quote> wildcard, but
matches single characters. Suppose that we have three files, 
<filename>file1.txt</filename>, <filename>file2.txt</filename> and
<filename>file3.txt</filename>. The string <emphasis>file?.txt</emphasis> 
matches all three of these files, but it does not match 
<filename>file10.txt</filename> (<quote>10</quote> are two characters).
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Matching characters from a set</title>

<para>
The <quote>[]</quote> wildcard matches every character between the brackets.
Suppose we have the files from the previous example,
<filename>file1.txt</filename>, <filename>file2.txt</filename> and
<filename>file3.txt</filename>. The string <emphasis>file[23].txt</emphasis>
matches <filename>file2.txt</filename> and <filename>file3.txt</filename>,
but not <filename>file1.txt</filename>.
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Redirections and pipes</title>

<para>
One of the main features of Unix-like shells are redirections and pipes. 
Before we start to look at both techniques we have to look how most Unix-like
commands work. When a command is not getting data from a file, it will open
a special pseudo-file named <emphasis>stdin</emphasis>, and wait for data
to appear on it. The same principle can be applied for command output, when
there is no explicit reason for saving output to a file, the pseudo-file
<emphasis>stdout</emphasis> will be opened for output of data. This principle
is shown schematically in <xref linkend="shell-inout" />
</para>

<figure id="shell-inout">
<title>Standard input and output</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/shell-inout.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
You can see <emphasis>stdin</emphasis> and <emphasis>stdout</emphasis>
in action with the <command>cat</command> command. If cat is started without
any parameters it will just wait for input on <emphasis>stdin</emphasis>
and output the same data on <emphasis>stdout</emphasis>. If no redirection
is used keyboard input will be used for <emphasis>stdin</emphasis>, and
<emphasis>stdout</emphasis> output will be printed to the terminal:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>cat</command>
<command>Hello world!</command>
Hello world!
</screen>

<para>
As you can see cat will print data to <emphasis>stdout</emphasis> after 
inputting data to <emphasis>stdin</emphasis> using the keyboard.
</para>

<sect3>
<title>Redirection</title>

<para>
The shell allows you to take use of <emphasis>stdin</emphasis> and
<emphasis>stdout</emphasis> using the <quote>&lt;</quote> and 
<quote>&gt;</quote>. Data is redirected in which way the sharp bracket
points. In the following example we will redirect the md5 summaries
calculated for a set of files to a file named 
<filename>md5sums</filename>:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>md5sum * > md5sums</command>
$ <command>cat md5sums</command> 
6be249ef5cacb10014740f61793734a8  test1
220d2cc4d5d5fed2aa52f0f48da38ebe  test2
631172a1cfca3c7cf9e8d0a16e6e8cfe  test3
</screen>

<para>
As we can see in the <command>cat</command> output the output of the
<command>md5sum *</command> output was redirected to the 
<filename>md5sums</filename> file. We can also use redirection to provide
input to a command:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>md5sum &lt; test1</command>
6be249ef5cacb10014740f61793734a8  -
</screen>

<para>
This feeds the contents of the <filename>test1</filename> to 
<command>md5sum</command>.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>pipes</title>

<para>
You can also connect the input and output of commands using so-called
<emphasis>pipes</emphasis>. A pipe between commands can be made with the
<quote>|</quote> character. Two or more combined commands are called a
<emphasis>pipeline</emphasis>. <xref linkend="shell-pipeline" /> shows
a schematic overview of a pipeline consisting of two commands.
</para>

<figure id="shell-pipeline">
<title>A pipeline</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/shell-pipeline.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
The <quote>syntax</quote> of a pipe is: <command>command1 | command2 ... |
commandn</command>. If you know how the most basic Unix-like commands work
you can now let these commands work together. Let's look at a quick example:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>cat /usr/share/dict/american-english | grep "aba" | wc -l</command>
123
</screen>

<para>
The first command, <command>cat</command>, reads the dictionary file
<filename>/usr/share/dict/american-english</filename>. The output of
the <command>cat</command> command is piped to <command>grep</command>,
which prints out all files containing the phrase <quote>aba</quote>.
In turn, the output of <quote>grep</quote> is piped to 
<command>wc -l</command>, which counts the number of lines it receives
from <emphasis>stdin</emphasis>. Finally, when the stream is finished
<command>wc</command> prints the number of lines it counted. So, combined
three commands to count the number of words containing the phrase
<quote>aba</quote> in this particular dictionary.
</para>

<para>
There are hundreds of small utilities that handle specific tasks. As you
can imagine, together these commands provide a very powerful toolbox by
making combinations using pipes.
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>

</chapter>
