<!-- $Id: inetd.xml,v 1.1 2004/11/06 23:17:47 daniel Exp $ -->

<chapter> <?dbhtml filename="inetd.html"?>
<title>The internet super server</title>

<sect1>
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
There are two ways to offer TCP/IP services: by running server
applications standalone as a daemon or by using the internet
super server, <command>inetd</command>(8). <command>inetd</command>
is a daemon which monitors a range of ports. If a client attempts
to connect to a port <command>inetd</command> handles the connection
and forwards the connection to the server software which handles
that kind of connection. The advantage of this approach is
that it adds an extra layer of security and it makes it easier
to log incoming connections. The disadvantage is that it is
somewhat slower than using a standalone daemon. It is thus
a good idea to run a standalone daemon on, for example, 
a heavily loaded FTP server.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Configuration</title>

<para>
<command>inetd</command> can be configured using the
<filename>/etc/inetd.conf</filename> file. Let's have a look at
an example line from <filename>inetd.conf</filename>:
</para>

<screen>
# File Transfer Protocol (FTP) server:
ftp     stream  tcp     nowait  root    /usr/sbin/tcpd  proftpd
</screen>

<para>
This line specifies that <command>inetd</command> should accept
FTP connections and pass them to <command>tcpd</command>. This
may seem a bit odd, because <command>proftpd</command> normally 
handles FTP connections. You can also specify to use <command>proftpd</command>
directly in <filename>inetd.conf</filename>, but Slackware normally
passes the connection to <command>tcpd</command>. This program
passes the connection to <command>proftpd</command> in turn, as specified.
<command>tcpd</command> is used to monitor services and to provide
host based access control.
</para>

<para>
Services can be disabled by adding the comment character (#) at
the beginning of the line. It is a good idea to disable all services
and enable services you need one at a time. After changing
<filename>/etc/inetd.conf</filename> <command>inetd</command>
needs to be restarted to activate the changes. This can be done
by sending the HUP signal to the inetd process:
</para>

<screen>
# <command>ps ax | grep 'inetd'</command>
   64 ?        S      0:00 /usr/sbin/inetd
# <command>kill -HUP 64</command>
</screen>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>TCP wrappers</title>

<para>
As you can see in <filename>/etc/inetd.conf</filename> connections for most
protocols are made through <command>tcpd</command>, instead of directly 
passing the connection to a service program. For example:
</para>

<screen>
# File Transfer Protocol (FTP) server:
ftp     stream  tcp     nowait  root    /usr/sbin/tcpd  proftpd
</screen>

<para>
In this example ftp connections are passed through <command>tcpd</command>.
<command>tcpd</command> logs the connection through syslog and allows for
additional checks. One of the most used features of <command>tcpd</command>
is host-based access control. Hosts that should be denied are controlled
via <filename>/etc/hosts.deny</filename>, hosts that should be allowed
via <filename>/etc/hosts.allow</filename>. Both files have one rule on
each line of the following form:
</para>

<screen>
service: hosts
</screen>

<para>
Hosts can be specified by hostname or IP address. The ALL keyword specifies
all hosts or all services.
</para>

<para>
Suppose we want to block access to all services managed through 
<command>tcpd</command>, except for host 
<quote>trusted.example.org</quote>. To do this the following
<filename>hosts.deny</filename> and <filename>hosts.allow</filename>
files should be created.
</para>

<para>
<filename>/etc/hosts.deny</filename>:
</para>

<screen>
ALL: ALL
</screen>

<para>
<filename>/etc/hosts.allow</filename>:
</para>

<screen>
ALL: trusted.example.org
</screen>

<para>
In the <filename>hosts.deny</filename> access is blocked to all (ALL)
services for all (ALL) hosts. But <filename>hosts.allow</filename>
specifies that all (ALL) services should be available to
<quote>trusted.example.org</quote>.
</para>

</sect1>

</chapter>
