<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
     xml:id="chap-install">
  <title>Instalando o Slackware Linux</title>

  <sect1 xml:id="chap-install-bootcd">
    <title>Inicializando pelo CD-ROM de instalação</title>

    <para>
      O método mais fácil para iniciar a instalação do sistema é
      utilizar o CD-ROM de instalação.  O CD-ROM de instalação do
      Slackware Linux é um CD inicializável, o que quer dizer que a BIOS
      pode inicializar a partir do CD, tal como poderia inicializar, por
      exemplo, a partir de um disco flexível.  A grande maioria dos
      sistemas modernos possuem BIOS com suporte a inicialização pelo
      CD-ROM.
    </para>

    <para>
      Se o CD não for inicializado quando você puder o CD no drive de
      CD-ROM durante a inicialização do sistema, provavelmente a
      sequência de inicialização não está adequadamente configurada na
      BIOS.  Entre na configuração da BIOS, também chamada de
      Setup (normalmente isto pode ser feito segurando-se a tecla
      &lt;Del&gt; ou então &lt;Esc&gt; quando a tela da BIOS aparece
      logo ao ligar o computador) e certifique-se de que CD-ROM esteja
      no topo da lista na sequência de inicialização.  Se você estiver
      usando um CD-ROM SCSI, você pode ter que definir a sequência de
      inicialização na BIOS SCSI ao invés de na BIOS do sistema.
      Consulte o manual de sua placa SCSI para mais informações.
    </para>

    <para>
      Quando o CD-ROM é inicializado, uma tela inicial irá aparecer.
      Normalmente você apenas pressiona &lt;ENTER&gt; carregando o
      kernel Linux padrão (<filename>hugesmp.s</filename>).  Este kernel
      precisa pelo menos de uma CPU Pentim Pro.  Você pode carregar um
      kernel alternativo digitando o nome do kernel no prompt, e
      pressionando &lt;ENTER&gt;.  A tabela a seguir lista os diferentes
      kernels que estão disponíveis no CD ou DVD do Slackware Linux.
    </para>

    <table xml:id="chap-install-bootcd-installkernels">
      <title>Kernels de installation</title>

      <tgroup cols="2">
    <thead>
      <row>
        <entry>Linux</entry><entry>Descrição</entry>
      </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <row>
        <entry>huge.s</entry>
        <entry>
          Anteriormente, havia kernels específicos para diferentes tipos
          de controladores de disco.  O novo kernel huge inclui suporte
          para todos os controladores ATA, SATA e SCSI mais comuns.
          Este kernel não tem suporte a SMP, e funciona em CPUs i486 ou
          superiores.  Se você tiver uma CPU Pentium Pro ou mais
          recente, é recomendado usar o kernel
          <emphasis>hugesmp.s</emphasis>, mesmo em sistemas com apenas
          um processador.
        </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>hugesmp.s</entry>
        <entry>
          O kernel <emphasis>hugesmp.s</emphasis> também tem suporte aos
          controladores ATA, SATA, e SCSI mais comuns.  Adicionalmente,
          este kernel oferece suporte a SMP.  Este é o kernel
          recomendado para CPUs Pentium Pro ou mais recentes.
        </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry>speakup.s</entry>
        <entry>
          Este kernel é comparável ao <emphasis>huge.s</emphasis>, mas
          também inclui suporte a hardwares sintetizadores de voz.
        </entry>
      </row>
    </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para>
      Depois de inicializar o sistema de instalação, você questionado
      sobre se está usando um leiaute de teclado especial (nacional) ou
      não.  Se você tiver um teclado US/Internacional normal, que é o
      tipo mais comum, você pode apenas apertar &lt;Enter&gt; nesta
      questão.  Depois disso, um prompt de login vai aparecer.  Efetue o
      login como usuário <quote>root</quote>, não será solicitada
      nenhuma senha.  Depois do login, o shell é iniciado e você pode
      começar a instalar o Slackware Linux.  O procedimento de
      instalação será explicado brevemente neste capítulo.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="chap-install-partitioning">
    <title>Particionando um disco rígido</title>

    <para>
      Instalar o Slackware Linux requer pelo menos uma partição Linux,
      mas a criação de uma partição de swap também é recomendada.  Para
      se criar uma partição, deve haver espaço livre não particionado no
      disco.  Há alguns programas que podem redimensionar partições.
      Como exemplo, o FIPS pode redimensionar partições FAT.  Programas
      comerciais como o Partition Magic também podem redimensionar
      outros tipos de partição.
    </para>

    <para>
      Depois de iniciar pelo CD-ROM do Slackware Linux e efetuar o
      login, haverá dois programas de particionamento à sua disposição:
      o <command>fdisk</command> e o<command>cfdisk</command>.  O
      <command>cfdisk</command> é o mais fácil dos dois, pois é
      controlado a partir de uma interface mais intuitiva com menus.
      Esta seção descreve o programa <command>cfdisk</command>.
    </para>

    <para>
      Para particionar o primeiro disco rígido você pode simplesmente
      executar <command>cfdisk</command>.  Se você quiser particionar
      outro disco ou um disco SCSI você tem que especificar qual disco
      você quer particionar (<command>cfdisk /dev/device</command>).
      Discos com hardware ATA têm dispositivos nomeados da seguinte
      forma: <filename>/dev/hdn</filename>, sendo <quote>n</quote>
      substituído por um caracter.  P.ex., o disco <quote>primário
      mestre</quote> (<foreignphrase>primary master</foreignphrase>) é
      chamado <filename>/dev/hda</filename>, enquanto que o
      <quote>secundário escravo</quote> (<foreignphrase>secondary
      slave</foreignphrase>) é chamado <filename>/dev/hdd</filename>.
      Discos SCSI são nomeados da seguinte forma:
      <filename>/dev/sdn</filename>, sendo <quote>n</quote> substituído
      por um caracter de dispositivo (com o primeiro disco SCSI = a, e
      o quarto disco SCSI = d).
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-partitioning-cfdisk">
      <title>A ferramenta de particionamento cfdisk</title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/cfdisk.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      Depois de executar o <command>cfdisk</command>, as partições
      atualmente existentes são mostradas, bem como o total de espaço
      livre.  A lista de partições pode ser navegada com as teclas de
      <quote>seta para cima</quote> e <quote>seta para baixo</quote>.
      Na parte de baixo da tela, são exibidos alguns comandos que podem
      ser navegados com as teclas de <quote>seta para esquerda</quote> e
      <quote>seta para direita</quote>.  Um comando pode ser executado
      com a tecla &lt;Enter&gt;.
    </para>

    <para>
      Você pode criar uma partição Linux selecionando o <quote>Free
      Space</quote> e executando o comando <quote>New</quote>.  O
      <command>cfdisk</command> irá lhe perguntar se você quer criar uma
      partição primária ou lógica.  Podem existir no máximo quatro
      partições primárias.  O Linux pode ser instalado tanto em
      partições primárias quanto em partições lógicas.  Se você quiser
      instalar outros sistemas operacionais além do Slackware Linux e
      que precise de uma partição lógica, é uma boa idéia instalar o
      Slackware Linux em uma partição lógica.  O tipo da nova partição é
      automaticamente definido como <quote>Linux Native</quote>, então
      não é necessário definir o tipo da partição.
    </para>

    <para>
      A criação de uma partição de troca
      (<foreignphrase>swap</foreignphrase>) envolve os mesmos passos que
      uma partição Linux normal, mas o tipo da partição deve ser trocado
      para <quote>Linux Swap</quote> depois que a partição for criada.
      O tamanho sugerido para uma partição de swap depende de suas
      próprias necessidades.  A partição de swap é usada para guardar
      programas se a memória principal (RAM) estiver cheia.  Se você
      tiver um disco rígido de tamanho razoável, é uma boa idéia deixar
      256MB ou 512MB para uma partição de swap, que deve ser o bastante
      para uso normal do computador.  Depois de criar a partição, o tipo
      da partição pode ser trocado para <quote>Linux Swap</quote>
      selecionando-se o comando <quote>Type</quote>.  O programa
      <command>cfdisk</command> irá lhe perguntar pelo número do tipo de
      partição.  Partições <quote>Linux Swap</quote> são do tipo número
      82.  Normalmente o número 82 já estará selecionado, então você
      pode prosseguir apenas pressionando a tecla &lt;Enter&gt;.
    </para>

    <para>
      Se você estiver satisfeito com o particionamento, você pode salvar
      as alterações executando o comando <quote>Write</quote>.  Esta
      operação precisa ser confirmada digitando-se
      <command>yes</command>.  Depois de salvar as alterações você pode
      sair do <command>cfdisk</command> com o comando
      <command>Quit</command>.  É recomendado reiniciar o computador
      antes de começar a instalação, para assegurar que as alterações do
      particionamento sejam efetivadas.  Pressione &lt;ctrl&gt; +
      &lt;alt&gt; + &lt;del&gt; para desativar o Linux e reiniciar o
      computador.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="chap-install-installing">
    <title>Installing Slackware Linux</title>

    <para>
      The Slackware Linux installer is started by executing
      <command>setup</command> in the installation disk shell. Setup
      will show a menu with several choices.  You can see a screenshot
      of the installer in <xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-setup"/>. Every
      option is required for a complete Slackware Linux installation,
      but once you start, the <command>setup</command> program will
      guide you through the options.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-setup">
      <title>A ferramenta setup</title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/setup.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The first part of the installation is named
      <quote>ADDSWAP</quote>. The <command>setup</command> tool will
      look for a partition with the <quote>Linux Swap</quote> type,
      and ask you if you want to format and activate the swap
      partition (see figure <xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-addswap"/>).
      Normally you can just answer <quote>Yes</quote>.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-addswap">
      <title>Definindo uma partição de swap</title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/addswap.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      After setting up the swap space the <quote>TARGET</quote> menu
      is launched, which you can see in <xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-partselect"/>. It is used to
      initialize the Slackware Linux partitions. Setup will display
      all partitions with the <quote>Linux Native</quote> type.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-partselect">
      <title>Selecionando uma partição para inicializar</title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/partselect.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      After selecting one partition, the setup tool will ask whether
      you want to format a partition or not, and if you want to format
      it, whether you want to check the disk for bad sectors or not
      (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-fscheck"/>). Checking
      the disk can take a lot of time.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-fscheck">
      <title>Formatando a partição</title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/fscheck.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      After selecting to format a partition, you can specify which
      filesystem should be used (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-filesystem"/>). Normally
      you can choose the ext2, ext3 and reiserfs filesystems. Ext2 was
      the standard Linux filesystem for many years, but it does not
      support journaling. A journal is a special file or area of a
      partition in which all filesystem operations are logged. When
      the system crashes, the filesystem can be repaired rapidly,
      because the kernel can use the log to see what disk operations
      were performed. Ext3 is the same filesystem as Ext2, but adds
      journaling. Reiserfs is a filesystem that also provides
      journaling. Reiserfs uses balanced trees, which make many
      filesystem operations faster than with Ext2 or Ext3, especially
      when working with many small files. A disadvantage is that
      Reiserfs is newer, and can be a bit more unstable.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-filesystem">
      <title>Selecionando um tipo de sistema de arquivos</title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/filesystem.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The first initialized partition is automatically mounted as the
      root (/) partition. For other partitions the mount point can be
      selected after the initialization. You could, for example, make
      separate partitions for <filename>/</filename>,
      <filename>/var</filename>, <filename>/tmp</filename>,
      <filename>/home</filename> and <filename>/usr</filename>. This
      provides extra protection against crashes. Since
      <filename>/</filename> is rarely changed after the installation
      if you create these partitions, the chance that it will be in
      the middle of a write operation during a crash is much smaller.
      Besides that, it is safer to create a separate filesystem for
      <filename>/home</filename>. If a program has a security
      vulnerability, a user could create a hard link to the binary of
      that program, if the <filename>/home</filename> directory is on
      the same filesystem as the <filename>/{s}bin</filename>
      <filename>/usr/{s}bin</filename>, or
      <filename>/usr/local/{s}bin</filename> directories. This user
      will then still be able to access the old, vulnerable binary
      after the program is upgraded.
    </para>

    <para>
      The next step is to select the source medium (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-medium"/>). This
      dialog offers several choices, like installing Slackware Linux
      from a CD-ROM or installing Slackware Linux via NFS. Slackware
      Linux is usually installed from CD-ROM, so this is what we are
      going to look at. After selecting <quote>CD-ROM</quote> you will
      be asked whether you want to let setup look for the CD-ROM
      itself (<quote>Auto</quote>) or you want to select the CD-ROM
      device yourself (<quote>Manual</quote>). If you select
      <quote>Manual</quote> the setup tool will show a list of
      devices. Select the device holding the Slackware Linux CD-ROM.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-medium">
      <title>Selecionando a mídia de instalação</title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/medium.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      After choosing an installation source the setup tool will ask
      you which disk sets (series) you want to install packages from
      (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-disksets"/>). A
      short description of each disk set is listed.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-disksets">
      <title>Selecionando as séries de discos de instalação</title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/disksets.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      Now it is almost time to start the real installation. The next
      screen asks how you would like to install. The most obvious
      choices are <quote>full</quote>, <quote>menu</quote> or
      <quote>expert</quote>.  Selecting <quote>full</quote> will
      install all packages in the selected disk sets. This is the
      easiest way of installing Slackware Linux.  The disadvantage of
      this choice is that it can take quite much disk space. The
      <quote>menu</quote> option will ask you for each disk set which
      packages you want to install. The <quote>expert</quote> option
      is almost equal to the <quote>menu</quote> option, but allows
      you to deselect some very important packages from the
      <quote>a</quote> disk set.
    </para>

    <para>
      After the completion of the installation the setup tool will
      allow you to configure some parts of the system. The first
      dialog will ask you where you would like to install the kernel
      from (see <xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-installkernel"
      />). Normally it is a good idea to install the kernel from the
      Slackware Linux CD-ROM, this will select the kernel you
      installed Slackware Linux with. You can confirm this, or select
      another kernel.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-installkernel">
      <title>Instalando o kernel</title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/kernel.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      At this point you can choose to make a bootdisk (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-bootdisk" />).  It
      is a good idea to make a bootdisk, you can use it to boot
      Slackware Linux if the LILO configuration is botched.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-bootdisk">
      <title>Criando um disco de inicialização</title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/bootdisk.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The following dialog can be used to make a link,
      <filename>/dev/modem</filename>, that points to your modem
      device. (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-modem" />). If you
      do not have a modem you can select <emphasis>no
      modem</emphasis>.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-modem">
      <title>Selecionando o modem padrão</title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/modem.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The next step is to select whether you would like to use hotplug
      (<xref linkend="chap-install-installing-hotplug"
      />).  Hotplug is used for automatically configuring pluggable
      USB, PCMCIA and PCI devices. Generally speaking, it is a good
      idea to enable hotplugging, but some systems may have problems
      with the probing of the hotplug scripts.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-hotplug">
      <title>Ativando conexões <quote>a quente</quote></title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/hotplug.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The following steps are important, the next dialogs will assist
      you with installing LILO, the Linux bootloader. Unless you have
      experience in configuring LILO it is a good idea to choose to
      use the <emphasis>simple</emphasis> option for configuration of
      LILO, which tries to configure LILO automatically (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-liloinstall" />).
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-liloinstall">
      <title>Selecionando o tipo de instalação do LILO</title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/lilo.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      After selecting the <emphasis>simple</emphasis> option the LILO
      configuration utility will asks you whether you would like to
      use a framebuffer or not (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-framebuffer" />).
      Using a framebuffer will allow you to use the console in several
      resolutions, with other dimensions than the usual 80x25
      characters. Some people who use the console extensively prefer
      to use a framebuffer, which allows them to keep more text on the
      screen. If you do not want a framebuffer console, or if you are
      not sure, you can choose <emphasis>standard</emphasis> here.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-framebuffer">
      <title>Escolhendo uma resolução de framebuffer</title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/framebuffer.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      After setting the framebuffer you can pass extra parameters to
      the kernel (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-kernel-param"
      />). This is normally not necessary, if you do not want to pass
      extra parameters you can just press the &lt;Enter&gt; key.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-kernel-param">
      <title>Adicionando parâmetros ao kernel</title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/kernel-param.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The last step of the LILO configuration is selecting where LILO
      should be installed (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-lilo-dest"
      />). <emphasis>MBR</emphasis> is the master boot record, the
      main boot record of PCs. Use this option if you want use
      Slackware Linux as the only OS, or if you want to use LILO to
      boot other operating systems. The <emphasis>Root</emphasis>
      option will install LILO in the boot record of the Slackware
      Linux <filename>/</filename> partition. Use this option if you
      use another bootloader.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-lilo-dest">
      <title>Escolhendo onde o LILO deve ser instalado</title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/lilo-dest.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      You will now be asked to configure your mouse. Select the mouse
      type from the dialog that appears (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-mouse" />).
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-mouse">
      <title>Configurando um mouse</title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/mouse.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      You will then be asked whether the <command>gpm</command>
      program should be loaded at boot time or not (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-ask-load-gpm" />).
      <command>gpm</command> is a daemon that allows you to cut and
      paste text on the console.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-ask-load-gpm">
      <title>Escolhendo se o GPM deve ser iniciado ou não</title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/ask-load-gpm.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The next few steps will configure network connectivity. This is
      required on almost every networked system. The Slackware Linux
      setup will ask you if you want to set up network connectivity
      (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-ask-configure-network"
      />). If you answer <quote>No</quote> you can skip the next few
      network-related steps.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-ask-configure-network">
      <title>Escolhendo se você quer configurar conexões de rede</title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/ask-configure-network.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      You will now be asked to set the hostname (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-hostname" />).
      Please note that this is not the fully qualified domain name
      (FQDN), just the part that represents the host (normally the
      characters before the first dot in a FQDN).
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-hostname">
      <title>Setting the host name</title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/hostname.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      After setting the host name you can set the domain name part of
      the fully qualified domain name (FQDN) (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-domainname" />).
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-domainname">
      <title>Definindo o nome de domínio</title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/domainname.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The rest of the network configuration steps depend on whether
      nodes in the network are configured to use a static or a dynamic
      IP address. Some networks have a DHCP server that automatically
      assigns an IP address to hosts in the network. If this is the
      case for the network the machine select
      <emphasis>DHCP</emphasis> during this step of the installation
      (<xref linkend="chap-install-installing-set-ipconfig-type"
      />). When DHCP is selected you will only be asked whether a host
      name should be sent to the server. Normally you can leave this
      blank. If you use DHCP you can skip the rest of the network
      configuration described below.
    </para>

    <para>
      If the network does not have a DHCP server you can choose the
      <emphasis>static IP</emphasis> option, which will allow you to
      set the IP address and related settings manually.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-set-ipconfig-type">
      <title>Configuração manual ou automática do endereço de IP</title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/set-ipconfig-type.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The first step of the manual configuration is to set the IP
      address of the first interface (eth0) of the machine (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-ipaddr" />).
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-ipaddr">
      <title>Definindo o endereço IP</title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/ipaddr.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      After setting the IP address you will be asked to enter the
      netmask.  The netmask is usually dependent on the IP address
      class (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-netmask" />).
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-netmask">
      <title>Definindo a máscara de rede</title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/netmask.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      You will then be asked to set the address of the gateway (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-gateway" />). The
      gateway is the machine on the network that provides access to
      other networks by routing IP packets. If your network has no
      gateway you can just hit the &lt;ENTER&gt; key.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-gateway">
      <title>Definindo o gateway</title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/gateway.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The next dialog will ask you whether you want to use a
      nameserver or not (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-ask-nameserver"
      />). A nameserver is a server that can provide the IP address
      for a hostname. For example, if you surf to
      <emphasis>www.slackbasics.org</emphasis>, the nameserver will
      <quote>convert</quote> the
      <emphasis>www.slackbasics.org</emphasis> name to the
      corresponding IP address.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-ask-nameserver">
      <title>Escolhendo se você quer ou não usar um servidor de nomes</title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/ask-nameserver.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      If you chose to use a nameserver, you will be given the
      opportunity to set the IP address of the nameserver (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-nameserver" />).
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-nameserver">
      <title>Definindo o(s) servidor(es) de nomes</title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/nameserver.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The final network settings screen provides an overview of the
      settings, giving you the opportunity to correct settings that
      have errors (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-network-confirm"
      />).
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-network-confirm">
      <title>Confirming the network settings</title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/network-confirm.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      After the network configuration you can set which services
      should be started (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-startup-services"
      />). You can mark/unmark services with the &lt;SPACE&gt; key.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-startup-services">
      <title>Habilitando/desabilitando serviços na inicialização</title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/startup-services.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <!-- try fonts? -->

    <para>
      Traditionally the system clock is set to the UTC timezone on
      UNIX(-like) systems. If this is the case, select
      <emphasis>Yes</emphasis> during the next step (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-ask-clock-utc"
      />). If you also use a non-UNIX(-like) OS on the same system,
      like Windows, it is usually a good idea to choose
      <emphasis>No</emphasis>, because some PC operating systems do
      not work with a separate system clock and software clock.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-ask-clock-utc">
      <title>Escolhendo se o relógio será ajustado para UTC</title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/ask-clock-utc.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      You will then be given the opportunity to select the time zone
      (<xref linkend="chap-install-installing-timezone"
      />). This is especially important on systems that have their
      system clock set to UTC, without selecting the correct timezone
      the software clock will not match the local time.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-timezone">
      <title>Configurando o fuso horário</title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/timezone.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      If you installed the X Window System you can now set the default
      window manager (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-defaultwm"
      />). The most basic functionality of a window manager is to
      provide basic window managing functionality like title bars. But
      some options, like KDE, provide a complete desktop environment.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-defaultwm">
      <title>Escolhendo o gerenciador de janelas padrão</title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/defaultwm.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The final step is to set the root password (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-rootpasswd" />).
      The setup will ask you whether you would like to set it or
      not. There is no reason not to do this, and without a root
      password your system is dangerously insecure.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-rootpasswd">
      <title>Definindo a senha do superusuário</title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/rootpasswd.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      At this point you have completed the Slackware Linux
      installation. You can now reboot the system to start your fresh
      new Slackware Linux system. It wasn't that hard, was it? ;-)
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-finished">
      <title>Concluído</title>
      <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="../images/finished.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
    </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
