<!-- $Id: latex.xml 261 2006-03-04 22:41:22Z danieldk $ -->

<chapter id="editing-latex"> <?dbhtml filename="latex.html"?>
  <title>LaTeX</title>

  <indexterm><primary>LaTeX</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm><primary>typesetting</primary></indexterm>

  <sect1 id="editing-latex-introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>
      LaTeX is a typesetting system that can be used to produce high-quality
      articles, books, letters and other publications. LaTeX is based on
      TeX, a lower-level typesetting language that was designed by Donald
      E. Knuth. LaTeX does not work like a <acronym>WYSIWYG</acronym>
      (what you see is what you get) word processor, the kind of document
      preparation system most people are accustomed to. With LaTeX you
      do not have to care about formatting the document, only about writing
      the document.
    </para>

    <para>
      LaTeX files are plain-text files that contain LaTeX macros. LaTeX
      formats the document based on the macros that are used. In the
      beginning using LaTeX may be a bit awkward to a new user. But after
      a while you will discover that using LaTeX has some distinct
      advantages. To name a few:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          LaTeX-formatted documents look very professional.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You do not have to care about the layout of your documents. You
          just add structure to your documents, and LaTeX takes care of
          the formatting.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          LaTeX files are plain text, and can easily be changed using
          standard UNIX tools, such as <command>vi</command>,
          <command>sed</command> or <command>awk</command>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          LaTeX provides very good support for typesetting things like
          mathematical formula, references and Postscript images.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      LaTeX is very extensive, so this chapter will only touch the
      surface of LaTeX. But it should be enough to get you started
      to be able to make simple documents.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="editing-latex-basic">
    <title>Preparing basic LaTeX documents</title>

    <indexterm><primary>LaTeX</primary><secondary>documentclass</secondary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>LaTeX</primary><secondary>environments</secondary></indexterm>

    <sect2 id="editing-latex-basic-minimal">
      <title>Minimal document structure</title>

      <para>
        Each LaTeX document has some basic minimal structure that
        describes the document. Let's look at an example:
      </para>

      <screen>
\documentclass[10pt,a4paper]{article} <co id="latex-struct-1" />

\title{The history of symmetric ciphers} <co id="latex-struct-2" />
\author{John Doe} <co id="latex-struct-3" />

\begin{document} <co id="latex-struct-4" />

This is a basic document. <co id="latex-struct-5" />

\end{document} <co id="latex-struct-6" />
      </screen>

      <para>
        You can already see the basic syntactical structure of LaTeX
        commands. A command is started with a backslash, followed by the
        name of the command. Each macro has a mandatory argument that
        is placed in accolades, and an optional argument that is placed
        in square brackets.
      </para>

      <calloutlist>
        <callout arearefs="latex-struct-1">
          <para>
            The first command in every document is the
            <emphasis>documentclass</emphasis>. This command specifies
            what kind of document LaTeX is dealing with. The type of
            document is specified as a mandatory parameter. You can
            also specify some optional parameters, such as the font
            size and the paper size. In this case the font size is changed
            from the default 12pt to 10pt, and A4 is used as the
            paper size. The document classes that are available in
            LaTeX are shown in <xref linkend="latex-documentclasses" />.
          </para>
        </callout>
        <callout arearefs="latex-struct-2">
          <para>
            After the documentclass you can add some meta-information
            to the document, like the title of the document. In this
            case the title is <emphasis>The history of symmetric 
            ciphers</emphasis>.
          </para>
        </callout>
        <callout arearefs="latex-struct-3">
          <para>
            The author command specifies the author of the book.
          </para>
        </callout>
        <callout arearefs="latex-struct-4">
          <para>
            The <emphasis>\begin</emphasis> command marks the beginning
            of an environment. There are many different environments,
            but they all implicate certain typesetting conventions for the
            text that is in an environment. In this case we start an
            <emphasis>document</emphasis> environment. This is a very
            basic environment, LaTeX interprets everything in this
            environment as the body of the text.
          </para>
        </callout>
        <callout arearefs="latex-struct-5">
          <para>
            The content of the document can be placed within the
            <emphasis>document</emphasis>, in this case a friendly
            warning about the nature of the document.
          </para>
        </callout>
        <callout arearefs="latex-struct-6">
          <para>
            All environments eventually have to be closed. The
            <emphasis>document</emphasis> environment is the last
            environment that is closed, because it denotes the end
            of the body of the text.
          </para>
        </callout>
      </calloutlist>

      <table id="latex-documentclasses">
        <title>LaTeX document classes</title>

        <tgroup cols="1">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Class</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>article</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>book</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>letter</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>report</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="editing-latex-basic-print">
      <title>Generating printable formats</title>

      <para>
        Once you have a LaTeX file, you can use the <command>latex</command>
        command to generate a <acronym>DVI</acronym> (Device Independent
        format) file:
      </para>

      <screen>
$ <command>latex crypto.tex</command>
This is pdfeTeX, Version 3.141592-1.21a-2.2 (Web2C 7.5.4)
entering extended mode
(./crypto.tex
LaTeX2e &lt;2003/12/01&gt;
Babel &lt;v3.8d&gt; and hyphenation patterns for american, french, german, ngerman, b
ahasa, basque, bulgarian, catalan, croatian, czech, danish, dutch, esperanto, e
stonian, finnish, greek, icelandic, irish, italian, latin, magyar, norsk, polis
h, portuges, romanian, russian, serbian, slovak, slovene, spanish, swedish, tur
kish, ukrainian, nohyphenation, loaded.
(/usr/share/texmf/tex/latex/base/article.cls
Document Class: article 2004/02/16 v1.4f Standard LaTeX document class
(/usr/share/texmf/tex/latex/base/size10.clo)) (./crypto.aux) [1] (./crypto.aux)
 )
 Output written on crypto.dvi (1 page, 248 bytes).
 Transcript written on crypto.log.
      </screen>

      <para>
        As the LaTeX command reports a DVI file is created after running
        the <command>latex</command> command. You can view this file with
        an X viewer for DVI files, <command>xdvi</command>:
      </para>

      <screen>
$ <command>xdvi crypto.dvi</command>
      </screen>

      <para>
        This file is not directly printable (although DVI files can be
        printed with <command>xdvi</command>). An ideal format for
        printable files is Postscript. You can generate a Postscript
        file from the DVI file with one simple command:
      </para>

      <screen>
$ <command>dvips -o crypto.ps crypto.dvi</command>
      </screen>

      <para>
        The <parameter class="command">-o</parameter> specifies the output
        (file) for the Postscript document. If this parameter is not
        specified, the output will be piped through <command>lpr</command>,
        which will schedule the document to be printed.
      </para>

      <para>
        <acronym>PDF</acronym> (Portable Document Format) is another
        popular format for electronic documents. PDF can easily be
        generated from Postscript:
      </para>

      <screen>
$ <command>ps2pdf crypto.ps</command>
      </screen>

      <para>
        The resulting output file will be the same as the input file,
        with the <filename>.ps</filename> extension replaced with
        <command>.pdf</command>.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="editing-latex-basic-sections">
      <title>Sections</title>

      <indexterm><primary>LaTeX</primary><secondary>sections</secondary></indexterm>

      <para>
        Now that you know how to create a basic LaTeX document, it is
        a good time to add some more structure. Structure is added using
        sections, subsections, and subsubsections. These structural
        elements are made with respectively the <emphasis>\section</emphasis>,
        <emphasis>\subsection</emphasis> and
        <emphasis>\subsubsection</emphasis> commands. The mandatory parameter
        for a section is the title for the section. Normal sections,
        subsections and subsubsections are automatically numbered, and
        added to the table of contents. By adding a star after a section
        command, for example <emphasis>\section*{title}</emphasis> section
        numbering is suppressed, and the section is not added to the
        table of contents. The following example demonstrates how
        you can use sections:
      </para>

      <screen>
\documentclass[10pt,a4paper]{article}

\title{The history of symmetric ciphers}
\author{John Doe}

\begin{document}

\section{Pre-war ciphers}

To be done.

\section{Modern ciphers}

\subsection*{Rijndael}

Rijndael is a modern block cipher that was designed by Joan Daemen and
Vincent Rijmen. 

In the year 2000 the US National Institute of Standards and Technologies
selected Rijndael as the winner in the contest for becoming the Advanced
Encryption Standard, the successor of DES.

\end{document}
      </screen>

      <para>
        The example above is pretty straightforward, but this is a good
        time to look at how LaTeX treats end of line characters and empty
        lines. Empty lines are ignored by LaTeX, making the text a
        continuous flow. An empty line starts a new paragraph. All paragraphs
        but the first paragraph are stared with a extra space left of the
        first word.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="editing-latex-basic-fontstyle">
      <title>Font styles</title>

      <para>
        Usually you may want to work with different font styles too. LaTeX
        has some commands that can be used to change the appearance of the
        current font. The most commonly used font commands are
        <emphasis>\emph</emphasis> for emphasized text, and
        <emphasis>\textbf</emphasis>. Have a look at <xref
        linkend="latex-fontstyles" /> for a more extensive list of font
        styles. Emphasis and bold text are demonstrated in this example
        paragraph:
      </para>

      <screen>
Working with font styles is easy. \emp{This text is emphasized} and
\textbf{this text is bold}.
      </screen>

      <table id="latex-fontstyles">
        <title>LaTeX font styles</title>

        <tgroup cols="2">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Command</entry>
              <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>\emph</entry>
              <entry>Add emphasis to a font.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>\textbf</entry>
              <entry>Print the text in bold.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>\textit</entry>
              <entry>Use an italic font.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>\textsl</entry>
              <entry>Use a font that is slanted.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>\textsc</entry>
              <entry>Use small capitals.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>\texttt</entry>
              <entry>Use a typewriter font.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>\textsf</entry>
              <entry>Use a sans-serif font.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>
</chapter>
