<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
	 xml:id="chap-install">
  <title>Instalando Slackware Linux</title>

  <sect1 xml:id="chap-install-bootcd">
    <title>Boteando el CD-ROM de instalación</title>

    <para>
      El método mas sencillo para botear el sistema es usando el
      CD-ROM de instalación. El CD-ROM de instalación de Slackware
      Linux es un CD boteable, esto quiere decir que la BIOS puede
      iniciar desde el CD, asi como puede iniciar desde discos
      floppy. La mayoría de los sistemas modernos tienen una BIOS que
      soporta el arranque desde CD-ROM.
    </para>

    <para>
      If the CD is not booted when you have the CD inserted in the
      CD-ROM drive during the system boot, the boot sequence is
      probably not correctly configured in the BIOS. Enter the BIOS
      setup (usually this can be done by holding the &lt;Del&gt; or
      &lt;Esc&gt; key when the BIOS screen appears) and make sure the
      CD-ROM is on the top of the list in the boot sequence.  If you
      are using a SCSI CD-ROM you may have to set the boot sequence in
      the SCSI BIOS instead of the system BIOS. Consult the SCSI card
      manual for more information.
    </para> 

    <para>
      When the CD-ROM is booted, a pre-boot screen will
      appear. Normally you can just press &lt;ENTER&gt; to proceed
      loading the default (<filename>hugesmp.s</filename>) Linux
      kernel. This kernel requires at least a Pentium Pro CPU. You can
      boot an alternative kernel by entering the kernel name on the
      prompt, and pressing &lt;ENTER&gt;.  The following table lists
      the different kernels that are available from the Slackware
      Linux CD or DVD.
    </para>

    <table xml:id="chap-install-bootcd-installkernels">
      <title>Installation kernels</title>

      <tgroup cols="2">
	<thead>
	  <row>
	    <entry>Linux</entry><entry>Description</entry>
	  </row>
	</thead>
	<tbody>
	  <row>
	    <entry>huge.s</entry>
	    <entry>
	      Previously, there were specific kernels for different
	      sets of disk controlers. The new huge kernels include
	      support for all common ATA, SATA and SCSI
	      controllers. This kernel does not have SMP support, and
	      works on i486 and newer CPUs. If you have a Pentium Pro
	      or newer CPU, it is recommended to use the
	      <emphasis>hugesmp.s</emphasis> kernel, even on
	      uniprocessor systems.
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry>hugesmp.s</entry>
	    <entry>
	      The <emphasis>hugesmp.s</emphasis> kernel has support
	      for common ATA, SATA, and SCSI
	      controllers. Additionally, this kernel has SMP
	      support. This is the recommended kernel on Pentium Pro
	      and newer CPUs.
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry>speakup.s</entry>
	    <entry>
	      This kernel is comparable to the
	      <emphasis>huge.s</emphasis> kernel, but also includes
	      support for hardware speech synthesizers.
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	</tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para>
      After booting the installation system, you will be asked whether
      you are using a special (national) keyboard layout or not. If
      you have a normal US/International keyboard, which is the most
      common, you can just press &lt;Enter&gt; at this question. After
      that the login prompt will appear. Log on as
      <quote>root</quote>, no password will be requested.  After
      login, the shell is started and you can begin installing
      Slackware Linux. The installation procedure will be explained
      briefly in this chapter.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="chap-install-partitioning">
    <title>Partitioning a hard disk</title>

    <para>
      Installing Slackware Linux requires at least one Linux
      partition, creating a swap partition is also recommended. To be
      able to create a partition there has to be free unpartitioned
      space on the disk. There are some programs that can resize
      partitions. For example, FIPS can resize FAT partitions.
      Commercial programs like Partition Magic can also resize other
      partition types.
    </para>

    <para>
      After booting the Slackware Linux CD-ROM and logging on, there
      are two partitioning programs at your disposal:
      <command>fdisk</command> and
      <command>cfdisk</command>. <command>cfdisk</command> is the
      easiest of both, because it is controlled by a menu
      interface. This section describes the <command>cfdisk</command>
      program.
    </para>

    <para>
      To partition the first harddisk you can simply execute
      <command>cfdisk</command>. If you want to partition another disk
      or a SCSI disk you have to specify which disk you want to
      partition (<command>cfdisk /dev/device</command>). ATA hard
      disks have the following device naming:
      <filename>/dev/hdn</filename>, with <quote>n</quote> replaced by
      a character. E.g. the <quote>primary master</quote> is named
      <filename>/dev/hda</filename>, the <quote>secondary
      slave</quote> is named <filename>/dev/hdd</filename>. SCSI disks
      are named in the following way: <filename>/dev/sdn</filename>,
      with <quote>n</quote> replaced by the device character (the
      first SCSI disk = a, the fourth SCSI disk = d).
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-partitioning-cfdisk">
      <title>The cfdisk parition tool</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/cfdisk.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      After starting <command>cfdisk</command>, the currently existing
      partitions are shown, as well as the amount of free space. The
      list of partitions can be navigated with the <quote>up</quote>
      and <quote>down</quote> arrow keys.  At the bottom of the screen
      some commands are displayed, which can be browsed with the
      <quote>left</quote> and <quote>right</quote> arrow keys.  A
      command can be executed with the &lt;Enter&gt; key.
    </para>

    <para>
      You can create a Linux partition by selecting <quote>Free
      Space</quote> and executing the <quote>New</quote>
      command. <command>cfdisk</command> will ask you whether you want
      to create a primary or logical partition.  The number of primary
      partitions is limited to four. Linux can be installed on both
      primary and logical partitions. If you want to install other
      operating systems besides Slackware Linux that require primary
      partitions, it is a good idea to install Slackware Linux onto a
      logical partition.  The type of the new partition is
      automatically set to <quote>Linux Native</quote>, so it is not
      necessary to set the partition type.
    </para>

    <para>
      The creation of a swap partition involves the same steps as a
      normal Linux partition, but the type of the partition has to be
      changed to <quote>Linux Swap</quote> after the partition is
      created. The suggested size of the swap partition depends on
      your own needs. The swap partition is used to store programs if
      the main (RAM) memory is full. If you have a harddisk of a
      reasonable size, it is a good idea to make a 256MB or 512MB swap
      partition, which should be enough for normal usage.  After
      creating the partition, the partition type can be changed to
      <quote>Linux Swap</quote> by selecting the <quote>Type</quote>
      command. The <command>cfdisk</command> program will ask for the
      type number. <quote>Linux Swap</quote> partitions have type
      number 82.  Normally number 82 is already selected, so you can
      go ahead by pressing the &lt;Enter&gt; key.
    </para> 

    <para>
      If you are satisfied with the partitioning you can save the
      changes by executing the <quote>Write</quote> command. This
      operation has to be confirmed by entering
      <command>yes</command>. After saving the changes you can quite
      <command>cfdisk</command> with the <command>Quit</command>
      command. It is a good idea to reboot the computer before
      starting the installation, to make sure that the partitioning
      changes are active.  Press &lt;ctrl&gt; + &lt;alt&gt; +
      &lt;del&gt; to shut Linux down and restart the computer.
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="chap-install-installing">
    <title>Installing Slackware Linux</title>

    <para>
      The Slackware Linux installer is started by executing
      <command>setup</command> in the installation disk shell. Setup
      will show a menu with several choices.  You can see a screenshot
      of the installer in <xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-setup"/>. Every
      option is required for a complete Slackware Linux installation,
      but once you start, the <command>setup</command> program will
      guide you through the options.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-setup">
      <title>The setup tool</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/setup.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The first part of the installation is named
      <quote>ADDSWAP</quote>. The <command>setup</command> tool will
      look for a partition with the <quote>Linux Swap</quote> type,
      and ask you if you want to format and activate the swap
      partition (see figure <xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-addswap"/>).
      Normally you can just answer <quote>Yes</quote>.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-addswap">
      <title>Setting up the swap partition</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/addswap.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      After setting up the swap space the <quote>TARGET</quote> menu
      is launched, which you can see in <xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-partselect"/>. It is used to
      initialize the Slackware Linux partitions. Setup will display
      all partitions with the <quote>Linux Native</quote> type.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-partselect">
      <title>Selecting a partition to initialize</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/partselect.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      After selecting one partition, the setup tool will ask whether
      you want to format a partition or not, and if you want to format
      it, whether you want to check the disk for bad sectors or not
      (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-fscheck"/>). Checking
      the disk can take a lot of time.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-fscheck">
      <title>Formatting the partition</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/fscheck.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      After selecting to format a partition, you can specify which
      filesystem should be used (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-filesystem"/>). Normally
      you can choose the ext2, ext3 and reiserfs filesystems. Ext2 was
      the standard Linux filesystem for many years, but it does not
      support journaling. A journal is a special file or area of a
      partition in which all filesystem operations are logged. When
      the system crashes, the filesystem can be repaired rapidly,
      because the kernel can use the log to see what disk operations
      were performed. Ext3 is the same filesystem as Ext2, but adds
      journaling. Reiserfs is a filesystem that also provides
      journaling. Reiserfs uses balanced trees, which make many
      filesystem operations faster than with Ext2 or Ext3, especially
      when working with many small files. A disadvantage is that
      Reiserfs is newer, and can be a bit more unstable.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-filesystem">
      <title>Selecting a filesystem type</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/filesystem.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The first initialized partition is automatically mounted as the
      root (/) partition. For other partitions the mount point can be
      selected after the initialization. You could, for example, make
      separate partitions for <filename>/</filename>,
      <filename>/var</filename>, <filename>/tmp</filename>,
      <filename>/home</filename> and <filename>/usr</filename>. This
      provides extra protection against crashes. Since
      <filename>/</filename> is rarely changed after the installation
      if you create these partitions, the chance that it will be in
      the middle of a write operation during a crash is much smaller.
      Besides that, it is safer to create a separate filesystem for
      <filename>/home</filename>. If a program has a security
      vulnerability, a user could create a hard link to the binary of
      that program, if the <filename>/home</filename> directory is on
      the same filesystem as the <filename>/{s}bin</filename>
      <filename>/usr/{s}bin</filename>, or
      <filename>/usr/local/{s}bin</filename> directories. This user
      will then still be able to access the old, vulnerable binary
      after the program is upgraded.
    </para>

    <para>
      The next step is to select the source medium (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-medium"/>). This
      dialog offers several choices, like installing Slackware Linux
      from a CD-ROM or installing Slackware Linux via NFS. Slackware
      Linux is usually installed from CD-ROM, so this is what we are
      going to look at. After selecting <quote>CD-ROM</quote> you will
      be asked whether you want to let setup look for the CD-ROM
      itself (<quote>Auto</quote>) or you want to select the CD-ROM
      device yourself (<quote>Manual</quote>). If you select
      <quote>Manual</quote> the setup tool will show a list of
      devices. Select the device holding the Slackware Linux CD-ROM.
    </para> 

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-medium">
      <title>Selecting the source medium</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/medium.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      After choosing an installation source the setup tool will ask
      you which disk sets (series) you want to install packages from
      (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-disksets"/>). A
      short description of each disk set is listed.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-disksets">
      <title>Selecting the disk sets</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/disksets.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      Now it is almost time to start the real installation. The next
      screen asks how you would like to install. The most obvious
      choices are <quote>full</quote>, <quote>menu</quote> or
      <quote>expert</quote>.  Selecting <quote>full</quote> will
      install all packages in the selected disk sets. This is the
      easiest way of installing Slackware Linux.  The disadvantage of
      this choice is that it can take quite much disk space. The
      <quote>menu</quote> option will ask you for each disk set which
      packages you want to install. The <quote>expert</quote> option
      is almost equal to the <quote>menu</quote> option, but allows
      you to deselect some very important packages from the
      <quote>a</quote> disk set.
    </para>

    <para>
      After the completion of the installation the setup tool will
      allow you to configure some parts of the system. The first
      dialog will ask you where you would like to install the kernel
      from (see <xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-installkernel"
      />). Normally it is a good idea to install the kernel from the
      Slackware Linux CD-ROM, this will select the kernel you
      installed Slackware Linux with. You can confirm this, or select
      another kernel.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-installkernel">
      <title>Installing the kernel</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/kernel.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      At this point you can choose to make a bootdisk (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-bootdisk" />).  It
      is a good idea to make a bootdisk, you can use it to boot
      Slackware Linux if the LILO configuration is botched.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-bootdisk">
      <title>Creating a bootdisk</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/bootdisk.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The following dialog can be used to make a link,
      <filename>/dev/modem</filename>, that points to your modem
      device. (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-modem" />). If you
      do not have a modem you can select <emphasis>no
      modem</emphasis>.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-modem">
      <title>Selecting the default modem</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/modem.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The next step is to select whether you would like to use hotplug
      (<xref linkend="chap-install-installing-hotplug"
      />).  Hotplug is used for automatically configuring pluggable
      USB, PCMCIA and PCI devices. Generally speaking, it is a good
      idea to enable hotplugging, but some systems may have problems
      with the probing of the hotplug scripts.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-hotplug">
      <title>Enabling hotplugging</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/hotplug.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The following steps are important, the next dialogs will assist
      you with installing LILO, the Linux bootloader. Unless you have
      experience in configuring LILO it is a good idea to choose to
      use the <emphasis>simple</emphasis> option for configuration of
      LILO, which tries to configure LILO automatically (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-liloinstall" />).
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-liloinstall">
      <title>Selecting the kind of LILO installation</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/lilo.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      After selecting the <emphasis>simple</emphasis> option the LILO
      configuration utility will asks you whether you would like to
      use a framebuffer or not (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-framebuffer" />).
      Using a framebuffer will allow you to use the console in several
      resolutions, with other dimensions than the usual 80x25
      characters. Some people who use the console extensively prefer
      to use a framebuffer, which allows them to keep more text on the
      screen. If you do not want a framebuffer console, or if you are
      not sure, you can choose <emphasis>standard</emphasis> here.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-framebuffer">
      <title>Choosing the framebuffer resolution</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/framebuffer.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      After setting the framebuffer you can pass extra parameters to
      the kernel (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-kernel-param"
      />). This is normally not necessary, if you do not want to pass
      extra parameters you can just press the &lt;Enter&gt; key.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-kernel-param">
      <title>Adding kernel parameters</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/kernel-param.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The last step of the LILO configuration is selecting where LILO
      should be installed (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-lilo-dest"
      />). <emphasis>MBR</emphasis> is the master boot record, the
      main boot record of PCs. Use this option if you want use
      Slackware Linux as the only OS, or if you want to use LILO to
      boot other operating systems. The <emphasis>Root</emphasis>
      option will install LILO in the boot record of the Slackware
      Linux <filename>/</filename> partition. Use this option if you
      use another bootloader.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-lilo-dest">
      <title>Choosing where LILO should be installed</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/lilo-dest.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      You will now be asked to configure your mouse. Select the mouse
      type from the dialog that appears (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-mouse" />).
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-mouse">
      <title>Configuring a mouse</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/mouse.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      You will then be asked whether the <command>gpm</command>
      program should be loaded at boot time or not (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-ask-load-gpm" />).
      <command>gpm</command> is a daemon that allows you to cut and
      paste text on the console.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-ask-load-gpm">
      <title>Choosing whether GPM should be started or not</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/ask-load-gpm.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The next few steps will configure network connectivity. This is
      required on almost every networked system. The Slackware Linux
      setup will ask you if you want to set up network connectivity
      (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-ask-configure-network"
      />). If you answer <quote>No</quote> you can skip the next few
      network-related steps.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-ask-configure-network">
      <title>Choosing whether you would like to configure network
      connectivity</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/ask-configure-network.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      You will now be asked to set the hostname (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-hostname" />).
      Please note that this is not the fully qualified domain name
      (FQDN), just the part that represents the host (normally the
      characters before the first dot in a FQDN).
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-hostname">
      <title>Setting the host name</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/hostname.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      After setting the host name you can set the domain name part of
      the fully qualified domain name (FQDN) (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-domainname" />).
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-domainname">
      <title>Setting the domain name</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/domainname.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The rest of the network configuration steps depend on whether
      nodes in the network are configured to use a static or a dynamic
      IP address. Some networks have a DHCP server that automatically
      assigns an IP address to hosts in the network. If this is the
      case for the network the machine select
      <emphasis>DHCP</emphasis> during this step of the installation
      (<xref linkend="chap-install-installing-set-ipconfig-type"
      />). When DHCP is selected you will only be asked whether a host
      name should be sent to the server. Normally you can leave this
      blank. If you use DHCP you can skip the rest of the network
      configuration described below.
    </para>

    <para>
      If the network does not have a DHCP server you can choose the
      <emphasis>static IP</emphasis> option, which will allow you to
      set the IP address and related settings manually.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-set-ipconfig-type">
      <title>Manual or automatic IP address configuration</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/set-ipconfig-type.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The first step of the manual configuration is to set the IP
      address of the first interface (eth0) of the machine (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-ipaddr" />).
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-ipaddr">
      <title>Setting the IP addres</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/ipaddr.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      After setting the IP address you will be asked to enter the
      netmask.  The netmask is usually dependent on the IP address
      class (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-netmask" />).
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-netmask">
      <title>Setting the netmask</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/netmask.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      You will then be asked to set the address of the gateway (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-gateway" />). The
      gateway is the machine on the network that provides access to
      other networks by routing IP packets. If your network has no
      gateway you can just hit the &lt;ENTER&gt; key.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-gateway">
      <title>Setting the gateway</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/gateway.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The next dialog will ask you whether you want to use a
      nameserver or not (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-ask-nameserver"
      />). A nameserver is a server that can provide the IP address
      for a hostname. For example, if you surf to
      <emphasis>www.slackbasics.org</emphasis>, the nameserver will
      <quote>convert</quote> the
      <emphasis>www.slackbasics.org</emphasis> name to the
      corresponding IP address.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-ask-nameserver">
      <title>Choosing whether you want to use a nameserver or not</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/ask-nameserver.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      If you chose to use a nameserver, you will be given the
      opportunity to set the IP address of the nameserver (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-nameserver" />).
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-nameserver">
      <title>Setting the nameserver(s)</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/nameserver.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The final network settings screen provides an overview of the
      settings, giving you the opportunity to correct settings that
      have errors (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-network-confirm"
      />).
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-network-confirm">
      <title>Confirming the network settings</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/network-confirm.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      After the network configuration you can set which services
      should be started (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-startup-services"
      />). You can mark/unmark services with the &lt;SPACE&gt; key.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-startup-services">
      <title>Enabling/disabling startup services</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/startup-services.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <!-- try fonts? -->

    <para>
      Traditionally the system clock is set to the UTC timezone on
      UNIX(-like) systems. If this is the case, select
      <emphasis>Yes</emphasis> during the next step (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-ask-clock-utc"
      />). If you also use a non-UNIX(-like) OS on the same system,
      like Windows, it is usually a good idea to choose
      <emphasis>No</emphasis>, because some PC operating systems do
      not work with a separate system clock and software clock.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-ask-clock-utc">
      <title>Choosing whether the clock is set to UTC</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/ask-clock-utc.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      You will then be given the opportunity to select the time zone
      (<xref linkend="chap-install-installing-timezone"
      />). This is especially important on systems that have their
      system clock set to UTC, without selecting the correct timezone
      the software clock will not match the local time.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-timezone">
      <title>Setting the timezone</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/timezone.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      If you installed the X Window System you can now set the default
      window manager (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-defaultwm"
      />). The most basic functionality of a window manager is to
      provide basic window managing functionality like title bars. But
      some options, like KDE, provide a complete desktop environment.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-defaultwm">
      <title>Choosing the default window manager</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/defaultwm.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The final step is to set the root password (<xref
      linkend="chap-install-installing-rootpasswd" />).
      The setup will ask you whether you would like to set it or
      not. There is no reason not to do this, and without a root
      password your system is dangerously insecure.
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-rootpasswd">
      <title>Setting the root password</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/rootpasswd.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      At this point you have completed the Slackware Linux
      installation. You can now reboot the system to start your fresh
      new Slackware Linux system. It wasn't that hard, was it? ;-)
    </para>

    <figure xml:id="chap-install-installing-finished">
      <title>Finished</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="../../images/finished.png" format="PNG" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
