<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
	 xml:id="chap-init">
  <title> Inicialización del sistema</title>

  <para>
    This chapter describes the initialization of Slackware
    Linux. Along the way various configuration files that are used to
    manipulate the initialization process are described.
  </para>

  <sect1 xml:id="chap-init-lilo">
    <title>The bootloader</title>

    <para>
      Arguably the most important piece of an operating system is the
      kernel. The kernel manages hardware resources and software
      processes.  The kernel is started by some tiny glue between the
      system <acronym>BIOS</acronym> (Basic Input/Output System) and
      the kernel, called the bootloader. The bootloader handles the
      complications that come with loading a specific (or less
      specific) kernel.
    </para>

    <para>
      Most bootloader actually work in two stages. The first stage
      loader loads the second stage loader, that does the real
      work. The boot loader is divided in two stages on x86 machines,
      because the BIOS only loads one sector (the so-called boot
      sector) that is 512 bytes in size.
    </para>

    <para>
      Slackware Linux uses the <acronym>LILO</acronym> (LInux LOader)
      boot loader. This bootloader has been in development since 1992,
      and is specifically written to load the Linux kernel. Lately
      LILO has been replaced by the <acronym>GRUB</acronym> (GRand
      Unified Bootloader) in most GNU/Linux distributions. GRUB is
      available as an extra package on the Slackware Linux
      distribution media.
    </para>

    <sect2 xml:id="chap-init-lilo-config">
      <title>LILO configuration</title>

      <para>
	LILO is configured through the
	<filename>/etc/lilo.conf</filename> configuration
	file. Slackware Linux provides an easy tool to configure
	LILO. This configuration tool can be started with the
	<command>liloconfig</command> command, and is described in the
	installation chapter (<xref linkend="chap-install-installing"
	/>).
      </para>

      <para>
	Manual configuration of LILO is pretty simple. The LILO
	configuration file usually starts off with some global
	settings:
      </para>

      <screen>
# Start LILO global section
boot = /dev/sda <co xml:id="liloconf-global-1" />
#compact        # faster, but won't work on all systems.
prompt <co xml:id="liloconf-global-2" />
timeout = 50 <co xml:id="liloconf-global-3" />
# Normal VGA console
vga = normal <co xml:id="liloconf-global-4" />
      </screen>

      <calloutlist>
	<callout arearefs="liloconf-global-1">
	  <para>
	    The <emphasis>boot</emphasis> option specifies where the
	    LILO bootloader should be installed. If you want to use
	    LILO as the main bootloader for starting Linux and/or
	    other operating systems, it is a good idea to install LILO
	    in the <acronym>MBR</acronym> (Master Boot Record) of the
	    hard disk that you use to boot the system. LILO is
	    installed to the MBR by omitting the partition number, for
	    instance <filename>/dev/hda</filename> or
	    <filename>/dev/sda</filename>.  If you want to install
	    LILO to a specific partition, add a partition number, like
	    <filename>/dev/sda1</filename>.  Make sure that you have
	    another bootloader in the MBR, or that the partition is
	    made active using <command>fdisk</command>.  Otherwise you
	    may end up with an unbootable system.
	  </para>

	  <para>
	    Be cautious if you use partitions with a XFS filesystem!
	    Writing LILO to an XFS partition will overwrite a part of
	    the filesystem. If you use an XFS root
	    (<filename>/</filename>) filesystem, create a non-XFS
	    <filename>/boot</filename> filesystem to which you install
	    LILO, or install LILO to the MBR.
	  </para>
	</callout>
	<callout arearefs="liloconf-global-2">
	  <para>
	    The <emphasis>prompt</emphasis> option will set LILO to
	    show a boot menu. From this menu you can select which
	    kernel or operating system should be booted. If you do not
	    have this option enabled, you can still access the
	    bootloader menu by holding the &lt;Shift&gt; key when the
	    bootloader is started.
            </para>
	</callout>
	<callout arearefs="liloconf-global-3">
	  <para>
	    The <emphasis>timeout</emphasis> value specifies how long
	    LILO should wait before the default kernel or OS is
	    booted.  The time is specified in tenths of a second, so
	    in the example above LILO will wait 5 seconds before it
	    proceeds with the boot.
	  </para>
	</callout>
	<callout arearefs="liloconf-global-4">
	  <para>
	    You can specify which video mode the kernel should use
	    with the <emphasis>vga</emphasis> option. When this is set
	    to <emphasis>normal</emphasis> the kernel will use the
	    normal 80x25 text mode.
	  </para>
	</callout>
      </calloutlist>

      <para>
	The global options are followed by sections that add Linux
	kernels or other operating systems. Most Linux kernel sections
	look like this:
      </para>

      <screen>
image = /boot/vmlinuz <co xml:id="co-liloconf-kernel-1" />
  root = /dev/sda5 <co xml:id="co-liloconf-kernel-2" /> 
  label = Slack <co xml:id="co-liloconf-kernel-3" />
  read-only <co xml:id="co-liloconf-kernel-4" />
      </screen>

      <calloutlist>
	<callout arearefs="co-liloconf-kernel-1">
	  <para>
	    The <emphasis>image</emphasis> option specifies the kernel
	    image that should be loaded for this LILO item.
	  </para>
	</callout>
	<callout arearefs="co-liloconf-kernel-2">
	  <para>
	    The <emphasis>root</emphasis> parameter is passed to the
	    kernel, and will be used by the kernel as the root
	    (<filename>/</filename>) filesystem.
	  </para>
	</callout>
	<callout arearefs="co-liloconf-kernel-3">
	  <para>
	    The <emphasis>label</emphasis> text is used as the label
	    for this entry in the LILO boot menu.
	  </para>
	</callout>
	<callout arearefs="co-liloconf-kernel-4">
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>read-only</emphasis> specifies that the root
	    filesystem should be mounted read-only. The filesystem has
	    to be mounted in read-only state to conduct a filesystem
	    check.
	  </para>
	</callout>
      </calloutlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="chap-init-lilo-installation">
      <title>LILO installation</title>

      <para>
	LILO does not read the <filename>/etc/lilo.conf</filename>
	file during the second stage. So, you will have to write
	changes to the second stage loader when you have changed the
	LILO configuration. This is also necessary if you install a
	new kernel with the same filename, since the position of the
	kernel on the disk may have changed. Reinstalling LILO can
	simply be done with the <command>lilo</command> command:
      </para>

      <screen>
# <command>lilo</command>
Added Slack26 *
Added Slack
      </screen>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="chap-init-init">
    <title>init</title>

    <para>
      After the kernel is loaded and started, the kernel will start
      the <command>init</command> command. <command>init</command> is
      the parent of all processes, and takes care of starting the
      system initialization scripts, and spawning login consoles
      through <command>agetty</command>. The behavior of
      <command>init</command> is configured in
      <filename>/etc/inittab</filename>.
    </para>

    <para>
      The <filename>/etc/inittab</filename> file is documented fairly
      well. It specifies what scripts the system should run for
      different runlevels. A runlevel is a state the system is running
      in. For instance, runlevel 1 is single user mode, and runlevel 3
      is multi-user mode. We will have a short look at a line from
      <filename>/etc/inittab</filename> to see how it works:
    </para>

    <screen>
rc:2345:wait:/etc/rc.d/rc.M
    </screen>

    <para>
      This line specifies that <command>/etc/rc.d/rc.M</command>
      should be started when the system switches to runlevel 2, 3, 4
      or 5.  The only line you probably ever have to touch is the
      default runlevel:
    </para>

    <screen>
id:3:initdefault:
    </screen>

    <para>
      In this example the default runlevel is set to
      <emphasis>3</emphasis> (multiuser mode). You can set this to
      another runlevel by replacing 3 with the new default
      runlevel. Runlevel 4 can particularly be interesting on desktop
      machines, since Slackware Linux will try to start the GDM, KDM
      or XDM display manager (in this particular order).  These
      display managers provide a graphical login, and are respectively
      part of GNOME, KDE and X11.
    </para>

    <para>
      Another interesting section are the lines that specify what
      command should handle a console. For instance:
    </para>

    <screen>
c1:1235:respawn:/sbin/agetty 38400 tty1 linux
    </screen>

    <para>
      This line specifies that <command>agetty</command> should be
      started on <emphasis>tty1</emphasis> (the first virtual
      terminal) in runlevels 1, 2, 3 and 5.  The
      <command>agetty</command> command opens the tty port, and
      prompts for a login name. <command>agetty</command> will then
      spawn <command>login</command> to handle the login. As you can
      see from the entries, Slackware Linux only starts one console in
      runlevel 6, namely <emphasis>tty6</emphasis>. One might ask what
      happened to <emphasis>tty0</emphasis>, <emphasis>tty0</emphasis>
      certainly exists, and represents the active console.
    </para>

    <para>
      Since <emphasis>/etc/inittab</emphasis> is the right place to
      spawn <command>agetty</command> instances to listen for logins,
      you can also let one or more agetties listen to a serial
      port. This is especially handy when you have one or more
      terminals connected to a machine. You can add something like the
      following line to start an <command>agetty</command> instance
      that listens on COM1:
    </para>

    <screen>
s1:12345:respawn:/sbin/agetty -L ttyS0 9600 vt100
    </screen>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="chap-init-initscripts">
    <title>Initialization scripts</title>

    <para>
      As explained in the <command>init</command> (<xref
      linkend="chap-init-init" />) section,
      <command>init</command> starts some scripts that handle
      different runlevels. These scripts perform jobs and change
      settings that are necessary for a particular runlevel, but they
      may also start other scripts. Let's look at an example from
      <filename>/etc/rc.d/rc.M</filename>, the script that
      <command>init</command> executes when the system switches to a
      multi-user runlevel:
    </para>

    <programlisting>
# Start the sendmail daemon:
if [ -x /etc/rc.d/rc.sendmail ]; then
  . /etc/rc.d/rc.sendmail start
fi
    </programlisting>

    <para>
      These lines say <quote>execute <command>/etc/rc.d/rc.sendmail
      start</command> if <filename>/etc/rc.d/rc.sendmail</filename> is
      executable</quote>. This indicates the simplicity of the
      Slackware Linux initialization scripts. Different functionality,
      for instance network services, can be turned on or off, by
      twiddling the executable flag on their initialization script.
      If the initialization script is executable, the service will be
      started, otherwise it will not. Setting file flags is described
      in <xref linkend="chap-filesystem-permissions-permbits" />, but
      we will have a look at a quick example how you can enable and
      disable sendmail.
    </para>

    <para>
      To start sendmail when the system initializes, execute:
    </para>

    <screen>
# <command>chmod +x /etc/rc.d/rc.sendmail</command>
    </screen>

    <para>
      To disable starting of sendmail when the system initializes,
      execute:
    </para>

    <screen>
# <command>chmod -x /etc/rc.d/rc.sendmail</command>
    </screen>

    <para>
      Most service-specific initialization scripts accept three
      parameters to change the state of the service:
      <emphasis>start</emphasis>, <emphasis>restart</emphasis> and
      <emphasis>stop</emphasis>. These parameters are pretty much self
      descriptive. For example, if you would like to restart sendmail,
      you could execute:
    </para>

    <screen>
# <command>/etc/rc.d/rc.sendmail restart</command>
    </screen>

    <para>
      If the script is not executable, you have to tell the shell that
      you would like to execute the file with
      <command>sh</command>. For example:
    </para>

    <screen>
# <command>sh /etc/rc.d/rc.sendmail start</command>
    </screen>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="chap-init-udev">
    <title>Hotplugging and device node management</title>

    <para>
      Slackware Linux has supported hotplugging since Slackware Linux
      9.1.  When enabled, the kernel passes notifications about device
      events to a userspace command. Since Slackware Linux 11.0,
      the <command>udev</command> set of utilities handle these
      notifications. <command>udev</command> manages the dynamic
      <filename>/dev</filename> directory as well.
    </para>

    <para>
      The mode of operation of <command>udev</command> for handling
      hotplugging of devices is fairly simple. When a device is added
      to the system, the kernel notifies userspace hotplug event
      listeners. <command>udev</command> will receive the notification
      of the device being added, and looks whether there are any
      module mappings for the device. If there are, the appropriate
      device driver module for the device is automatically
      loaded. <command>udev</command> will remove the module when it
      is notified of a device removal, and no devices use the loaded
      module anymore.
    </para>

    <para>
      The udev subsystem is initialized in
      <filename>/etc/rc.d/rc.S</filename> by executing
      <command>/etc/rc.d/rc.udev start</command>. As with most
      functionality, you can enable or disable udev by twiddling the
      executable flag of the <filename>/etc/rc.d/rc.udev</filename>
      script (see <xref linkend="chap-init-initscripts" />).
    </para>

    <para>
      If udev automatically loads modules that you do not want to
      load, you can add a <emphasis>blacklist</emphasis> in your
      <command>modprobe</command> configuration in
      <filename>/etc/modprobe.d/blacklist</filename>. For example, if
      you would like to prevent loading of the
      <emphasis>8139cp</emphasis> module, you can add the following
      line (actually, this module is already blacklisted in Slackware
      Linux):
    </para>

    <screen>
blacklist 8139cp
    </screen>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="chap-init-firmware">
    <title>Device firmware</title>

    <sect2 xml:id="chap-init-firmware-introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <para>
	Some hardware requires the system to upload firmware. Firmware
	is a piece of software that is used to control the hardware.
	Traditionally, the firmware was stored permanently in ROM
	(read-only memory) or non-volatile media like flash memory.
	However, many new devices use volatile memory to store
	firmware, meaning that the firmware needs to be reloaded to
	the device memory when the system is restarted.
      </para>

      <para>
	Drivers for devices that require firmware have a table of the
	firmware files that it needs. For each firmware file that the
	driver needs, it will issue a firmware addition event. If udev
	handles hotplugging events, it will try to handle that event.
	The udev rules contain an entry for firmware addition events
	in <filename>/etc/udev/rules.d/50-udev.rules</filename>:
      </para>

      <programlisting>
# firmware loader
SUBSYSTEM=="firmware", ACTION=="add", RUN+="/lib/udev/firmware.sh"
      </programlisting>

      <para>
	This means that upon firmware addition events, the
	<filename>/lib/udev/firmware.sh</filename> script should be
	executed. This script searches the
	<filename>/lib/firmware</filename> and
	<filename>/usr/local/lib/firmware</filename> directories for
	the requested firmware. If the firmware file exists, it will
	be loaded by copying the contents of the file to a special
	sysfs node.
      </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 xml:id="chap-init-firmware-adding">
      <title>Adding firmware</title>

      <para>
	As described in the previous section, some hardware requires
	firmware to be uploaded to hardware by the operating system.
	If this is the case, and no firmware is installed, the kernel
	will emit an error message when the driver for that hardware
	is loaded. You can see the kernel output with the
	<command>dmesg</command> command or in the
	<filename>/var/log/messages</filename> log file. Such error
	message explicitly says that the firmware could not be loaded,
	for example:
      </para>

      <screen>
ipw2100: eth1: Firmware 'ipw2100-1.3.fw' not available or load failed.
ipw2100: eth1: ipw2100_get_firmware failed: -2 
      </screen>

      <para>
	In this case you will have to find the firmware for your
	device. This can usually be found by searching the web for the
	chipset or driver for the device (in this case
	<emphasis>ipw2100</emphasis>) and the literal term
	<quote>firmware</quote>. The firmware archive often contains a
	file with installation instructions. Usually you can just copy
	the firmware files to <filename>/lib/firmware</filename>.
      </para>

      <para>
	After installing the firmware, you can reload the driver with
	<command>rmmod</command> and <command>modprobe</command>, or
	by restarting the system.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

<!-- XXX - udev rules sections should be added here <sect2
     xml:id="chap-init-hotplug-hooks"> <title>Executing scripts on
     hotplug events</title>

      <para>
	One of the useful aspects of the hotplug scripts is that you
	can execute scripts when a device is added or removed. When a
	device event occurs, hotplug will execute all scripts with the
	<filename>.hotplug</filename> suffix in
	<filename>/etc/hotplug.d/&lt;class&gt;/</filename>, in which
	<emphasis>&lt;class&gt;</emphasis> denotes the class in which
	the device is in that caused the event. There most important
	classes are:
      </para>

      <table>
	<title>Hotplug device classes</title>

	<tgroup cols="2">
	  <thead>
	    <row>
	      <entry>Prefix</entry><entry>Description</entry>
	    </row>
	  </thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <row>
	      <entry>default</entry>
	      <entry>Scripts for this device class are started
	      after any hotplug event.</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>ieee1394</entry>
	      <entry>IEEE1394/Firewire devices.</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>input</entry>
	      <entry>Input devices like keyboards and mice.</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>net</entry>
	      <entry>Network devices. Network devices will also
	      trigger bus-specific hotplug events.</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>pci</entry>
	      <entry>Devices on the PCI bus.</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>scsi</entry>
	      <entry>SCSI disks, CD-ROM and tape devices.</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>usb</entry>
	      <entry>Devices that use the USB bus.</entry>
	    </row>
	  </tbody>
	</tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>
	Besides the device class, there is something some other
	convention that is worth observing: it is best to add a number
	and a dash as a prefix to the script, because this will allow
	you to order the priority of the scripts. For example,
	<filename>10-dosomething.hotplug</filename> will be executed
	before <filename>20-dosomething.hotplug</filename>.
      </para>

      <note>
	<para>
	  There is black no magic going on with the priority of the
	  script :^). <filename>/sbin/hotplug</filename> uses a
	  wildcard to loop through the scripts, and
	  <filename>10</filename> matches earlier than
	  <filename>20</filename>:
	</para>

	<programlisting>
for I in "${DIR}/$1/"*.hotplug "${DIR}/"default/*.hotplug ; do
	</programlisting>

	<para>
	  Hopefully this will give some taste of the power of shell
	  scripting.
	</para>
      </note>

      <para>
	Now, let's look at an example stub script, that does nothing
	besides outputting debug messages:
      </para>

      <programlisting>
#!/bin/sh

cd /etc/hotplug
. ./hotplug.functions

DEBUG=yes export DEBUG

debug_mesg "arguments ($*) env (`env`)"

case $ACTION in
  add|register)
    # Stub 
  ;;
  remove|unregister)
    # Stub 
  ;;
esac
      </programlisting>

      <para>
	By default, the hotplug scripts log at the
	<emphasis>notice</emphasis> level. The standard syslog
	configuration on Slackware Linux does not log this. To debug
	hotplugging scripts, it is best to change the logging
	level. You can do this by replacing the following line in
	<filename>/etc/hotplug/hotplug.functions</filename>:
      </para>

      <programlisting>
$LOGGER -t $(basename $0)"[$$]" "$@"
      </programlisting>

      <para>
	to:
      </para>

      <programlisting>
$LOGGER -p user.info -t $(basename $0)"[$$]" "$@"
      </programlisting>

      <para>
	After this change hotplug debug messages will be visible in
	<filename>/var/log/messages</filename>.
      </para>

      <para>
	As you can see the script makes use of the
	<emphasis>$ACTION</emphasis> variable to see what kind of
	hotplug action took place. Let's take a look at an example
	action when this script is used for handling USB events, and
	named <filename>10-stub.hotplug</filename>:
      </para>

      <screen>
Jul 19 16:13:23 mindbender 10-stub.hotplug[18970]: arguments (usb) env
(SUBSYSTEM=usb OLDPWD=/ DEVPATH=/devices/pci0000:00/0000:00:10.0/usb2/2-1/2-1.3/2-1.3:1.2
PATH=/bin:/sbin:/usr/sbin:/usr/bin ACTION=add PWD=/etc/hotplug HOME=/ SHLVL=2
DEVICE=/proc/bus/usb/002/009 PHYSDEVDRIVER=snd-usb-audio INTERFACE=1/2/0
PRODUCT=d8d/651/1 TYPE=0/0/0 DEBUG=yes PHYSDEVBUS=usb SEQNUM=1528 _=/usr/bin/env)
      </screen>

      <para>
	That is nice, when I plugged an USB device, the script gets
	loaded (a couple of times, this is just one of the interesting
	bits).  Actually, this is my USB Phone, which is represented
	as an USB audio device under GNU/Linux. The problem with USB
	audio devices is that the device volumes that are saved with
	<command>alsactl store</command> are not automatically set
	when the device is plugged. But right know we can easily
	execute <command>alsactl restore</command> when the device is
	plugged. Please note that the script gets very useful
	information through some environment variables.
      </para>

      <para>
	To solve the volume problem, we can create a script, say
	<filename>/etc/hotplug.d/usb/50-usb-audio-volume.hotplug</filename>,
	that looks like this:
      </para>

      <programlisting>
#!/bin/sh

cd /etc/hotplug
. ./hotplug.functions
# DEBUG=yes export DEBUG

debug_mesg "arguments ($*) env (`env`)"

case $ACTION in
  add|register)
    if [ $PHYSDEVDRIVER = "snd-usb-audio" ]; then
      /usr/sbin/alsactl restore
    fi
  ;;
  remove|unregister)
  ;;
  *)
    debug_mesg "Unknown action '$ACTION'"
  ;;
esac
      </programlisting>

      <para>
	Based on the environment variables this script can be refined
	to restrict running <command>alsactl</command> for specific
	USB audio devices.
      </para>
    </sect2>
-->
</chapter>
