<!-- $Id: printing.xml 283 2007-09-18 20:14:31Z danieldk $ -->

<chapter id="printing"> <?dbhtml filename="printer.html"?>
  <title>Configuración de impresora</title>

  <indexterm><primary>printing</primary></indexterm>

  <sect1 id="printing-intro">
    <title>Introducción</title>

    <indexterm><primary>cups</primary><secondary>installation</secondary></indexterm>

    <para>
	  GNU/Linux soporta una gran cantidad de impresoras USB, paralelas y 
	  de red. Slackware Linux provee dos sistemas de impresión, 
	  <acronym>CUPS</acronym> (Common UNIX Printing System) y
      <acronym>LPRNG</acronym> (LPR Next Generation). Este capítulo cubre 
	  el sistema CUPS.
    </para>

    <para>
	  Independientemente de que sistema de impresión vaya a usar, es una 
	  buena idea instalar algunas colecciones de filtro de impresora. Estos 
	  se encuentran en el directorio de paquetes <quote>ap</quote>. Si quiere 
	  tener soporte para la mayoría de las impresoras, asegúrese de que los 
	  siguientes paquetes esten instalados:
    </para>

    <screen>
a2ps
enscript
espgs
gimp-print
gnu-gs-fonts
hpijs
ifhp
    </screen>

    <para>
	  Ambos sistemas tiene sus propias ventajas y desventajas. Si no tiene mucha 
	  experiencia configurando impresoras bajo GNU/Linux, es una buena idea usar 
	  CUPS, ya que CUPS provee una confortable interfaz web que puede ser accedida 
	  a través de un navegador web.
    </para> 

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="printing-preparations">
    <title>Preparaciones</title>

    <indexterm><primary>cups</primary><secondary>starting</secondary></indexterm>

    <para>
	  Para poder utilizar CUPS, el paquete <quote>cups</quote> de el 
	  conjunto de paquetes <quote>a</quote> debe ser instalado. Despues 
	  de la instalación, CUPS puede ser iniciado automáticamente desde 
	  el arranque del sistema haciendo el archivo <filename>/etc/rc.d/rc.cups</filename> 
	  ejecutable. Esto se realiza ejecutando el siguiente comando: 
    </para>

    <screen>
# <command>chmod a+x /etc/rc.d/rc.cups</command>
    </screen>

    <para>
	  Después de reiniciar el sistema, CUPS también sera reiniciado automáticamente. 
	  Puede iniciar CUPS en un sistema en ejecución con el siguiente comando:
    </para>

    <screen>
# <command>/etc/rc.d/rc.cups start</command>
    </screen> 

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="printing-configuration">
    <title>Configuración</title>

    <indexterm><primary>cups</primary><secondary>configuration</secondary></indexterm>

    <para>
	  CUPS puede ser configurado a través de una interfaz web. La interfaz de 
	  configuración puede ser accedida con un navegador web en la siguiente 
	  URL: <ulink url="http://localhost:631/">http://localhost:631/</ulink>. 
	  Algunas partes de la interfaz web requieren autenticación. Si una ventana 
	  de autenticación es mostrada, puede ingresar <quote>root</quote> como 
	  nombre de usuario y su correspondiente contraseña.
    </para>

    <para>
	  Una impresora puede ser agregada a la configuración CUPS a través del 
	  menu <quote>Administrate</quote>, y luego seleccionando el boton <quote>Add
      Printer</quote>. La interfaz web preguntará por tres opciones:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Name</emphasis> - the name of the printer. Use a simple
          name, for example <quote>epson</quote>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Location</emphasis> - the physical location of the printer.
          This setting is not crucial, but handy for larger organizations.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Description</emphasis> - a description of the printer,
          for example <quote>Epson Stylus Color C42UX</quote>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist> 

    <para>
	  Puede proceder presionando en el boton <quote>Continue</quote>. En 
	  la siguiente página puede configurar la conexion de la impresora. Si 
	  tiene una impresora USB encendida, la interfaz web mostrará el nombre 
	  de la impresora junto al puerto USB usado. Después de configurar el 
	  puerto de la impresora puede seleccionar su marca y modelo. Después 
	  de eso, la configuración está finalizada y la impresora será agregada 
	  a la configuración CUPS.
    </para>

    <para>	
      An overview of the configured printers can be found on the
      <quote>Printers</quote> page. On this page you can also do some
      printer operations. For example, <quote>Print Test Page</quote>
      can be used to check the printer configuration by printing a test
      page.
    </para>

  </sect1>
  
  <sect1 id="printing-accesscontrol">
    <title>Access control</title>

    <indexterm><primary>cups</primary><secondary>access control</secondary></indexterm>
    
    <para>
      The CUPS printing system provides a web configuration interface, and
      remote printer access through the Internet Printing Protocol 
      (<acronym>IPP</acronym>). The CUPS configuration files allow you
      to configure fine-grained access control to printers. By default access 
      to printers is limited to <emphasis>localhost</emphasis>
      (<emphasis>127.0.0.1</emphasis>).
    </para>
    
    <para>
      You can refine access control in the central CUPS daemon configuration
      file, <filename>/etc/cups/cupsd.conf</filename>, which has a syntax
      that is comparable to the Apache configuration file. Access control
      is configured through <emphasis>Location</emphasis> sections. For
      example, the default global (IPP root directory) section looks like
      this:
    </para>
    
    <screen>
&lt;Location /&gt;
Order Deny,Allow
Deny From All
Allow From 127.0.0.1
&lt;/Location&gt;
    </screen>

    <para>
      As you can see deny statements are handled first, and then allow
      statements. In the default configuration access is denied from
      all hosts, except for <emphasis>127.0.0.1</emphasis>, 
      <emphasis>localhost</emphasis>. Suppose that you would like to
      allow hosts from the local network, which uses the 
      <emphasis>192.168.1.0/24</emphasis> address space, to use the
      printers on the system you are configuring CUPS on. In this
      case you could add the line that is bold:
    </para>

    <screen>
&lt;Location /&gt;
Order Deny,Allow
Deny From All
Allow From 127.0.0.1
<emphasis role="bold">Allow From 192.168.1.0/24</emphasis>
&lt;/Location&gt;
    </screen>

    <para>
      You can refine other locations in the address space by adding
      additional location sections. Settings for sub-directories override
      global settings. For example, you could restrict access to the
      <emphasis>epson</emphasis> printer to the hosts with IP addresses
      <emphasis>127.0.0.1</emphasis> and <emphasis>192.168.1.203</emphasis>
      by adding the following section:
    </para>

    <screen>
&lt;Location /printers/epson&gt;
Order Deny,Allow
Deny From All
Allow From 127.0.0.1
Allow From 192.168.1.203
&lt;/Location&gt;
    </screen>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="printing-gspapersize">
    <title>Ghostscript paper size</title>

    <indexterm><primary>Ghostscript</primary><secondary>paper size</secondary></indexterm>

    <para>
      Ghostscript is a PostStript and Portable Document Format
      (<acronym>PDF</acronym>) interpreter. Both PostScript and
      PDF are languages that describe data that can be printed.
      Ghostscript is used to
      convert PostScript and PDF to raster formats that can be
      displayed on the screen or printed. Most UNIX programs
      output PostScript, the CUPS spooler uses GhostScript to convert
      this PostScript to rasterized format that a particular printer
      understands.
    </para>

    <para>
      There are some Ghostscript configuration settings that may
      be useful to change in some situations. This section describes
      how you can change the default paper size that Ghostscript
      uses.
    </para>

    <note>
      <para>
        Some higher-end printers can directly interpret PostScript.
        Rasterization is not needed for these printers.
      </para>
    </note>

    <para>
      By default Ghostscript uses US letter paper as the default
      paper size. The paper size is configured in
      <filename>/usr/share/ghostscript/x.xx/lib/gs_init.ps</filename>,
      in which <emphasis>x.xx</emphasis> should be replaced by
      the Ghostscript version number. Not far after the beginning
      of the file there are two lines that are commented out with
      a percent (%) sign, that look like this:
    </para>

    <screen>
% Optionally choose a default paper size other than U.S. letter.
% (a4) /PAPERSIZE where { pop pop } { /PAPERSIZE exch def } ifelse
    </screen>

    <para>
      You can change the Ghostscript configuration to use A4 as the
      default paper size by removing the percent sign and space that 
      are at the start of the second line, changing it to:
    </para>

    <screen>
% Optionally choose a default paper size other than U.S. letter.
(a4) /PAPERSIZE where { pop pop } { /PAPERSIZE exch def } ifelse
    </screen>

    <para>
      It is also possible to use another paper size than Letter or
      A4 by replacing <emphasis>a4</emphasis> in the example above
      with the paper size you want to use. For example, you could
      set the default paper size to US Legal with:
    </para>

    <screen>
% Optionally choose a default paper size other than U.S. letter.
(legal) /PAPERSIZE where { pop pop } { /PAPERSIZE exch def } ifelse
    </screen>

    <para>
      It is also possible to set the paper size per invocation of
      Ghostscript by using the
      <parameter class="command">-sPAPERSIZE=size</parameter> parameter
      of the <command>gs</command> command. For example, you could
      use add <emphasis>-sPAPERSIZE=a4</emphasis> parameter when you
      start <command>gs</command> to use A4 as the paper size for an
      invocation of Ghostscript.
    </para>

    <para>
      An overview of supported paper sizes can be found in the
      <filename>gs_statd.ps</filename>, that can be found in the
      same directory as <filename>gs_init.ps</filename>.
    </para>
  </sect1>

</chapter>
