<!-- $Id: x11.xml,v 1.1 2004/11/06 23:17:47 daniel Exp $ -->

<chapter> <?dbhtml filename="x11.html"?>
<title>X11</title>

<sect1>
<title>X Configuration</title>

<para>
The X11 configuration is stored in <filename>/etc/X11/xorg.conf</filename>.
Many distributions provide special configuration tools for X, but Slackware
Linux only provides the standard X11 tools (which are actually quite
easy to use). In most cases X can be configured automatically, but sometimes
it is necessary to edit <filename>/etc/X11/xorg.conf</filename> manually.
</para>

<bridgehead>Automatical configuration</bridgehead>

<para>
The X11 server provides an option to automatically generate a
configuration file. X11 will load all available driver modules,
and will try to detect the hardware, and generate a configuration
file. Execute the following command to generate a 
<filename>xorg.conf</filename> configuration file:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>X -configure</command>
</screen>

<para>
If X does not output any errors, the generated configuration can be
copied to the <filename>/etc/X11</filename> directory. And X can be
started to test the configuration:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>cp /root/xorg.conf /etc/X11/</command>
$ <command>startx</command>
</screen>

<bridgehead>Interactive configuration</bridgehead>

<para>
X11 provides two tools for configuring X interactively,
<command>xorgcfg</command> and <command>xorgconfig</command>.
<command>xorgcfg</command> tries to detect the video card automatically,
and starts a tool which can be used to tune the configuration.
Sometimes <command>xorgcfg</command> switches to a video mode which
is not supported by the monitor. In that case <command>xorgcfg</command>
can also be used in text-mode, by starting it with
<command>xorgcfg -textmode</command>.
</para>  

<para>
<command>xorgconfig</command> differs from the tools described above,
it does not detect hardware and will ask detailed questions about
your hardware. If you only have little experience configuring X11
it is a good idea to avoid <command>xorgconfig</command>.
</para> 

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Window manager</title>

<para>
The "look and feel" of X11 is managed by a so-called window manager.
Slackware Linux provides the following widely user window managers:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
WindowMaker: A relatively light window manager, which is part of the GNUStep
project.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
BlackBlox: Light window manager, BlackBox has no dependencies except the
X11 libraries.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
KDE: A complete desktop environment, including browser, e-mail program
and an office suite (KOffice).
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
GNOME: Like KDE a complete desktop environment. It is worth noting that
<ulink url="http://www.dropline.net/">Dropline Systems</ulink> provides
a special GNOME environment for Slackware.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
If you are used to a desktop environment, using KDE or GNOME is a logical
choice. But it is a good idea to try some of the lighter
window managers. They are faster, and consumer less memory, besides that
most KDE and GNOME applications are perfectly usable under other window
managers.
</para>

<para>
On Slackware Linux the following command can be used to select a window
manager:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>xwmconfig</command>
</screen>

<para>
This configuration program shows the installed window managers, from which
you can choose one. You can set the window manager globally by executing
<command>xwmconfig</command> as root.
</para>

</sect1>

</chapter>
